<section id="blueLive">
  <title>Blue Live</title>

  <screenshot>
    <screeninfo>Blue Live</screeninfo>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/blueLive.png" format="PNG" 
                   scalefit="1" 
                   width="100%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>Blue Live</phrase>
      </textobject>
      <caption>
        <para>Blue Live</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>

  <para>
    Blue Live allows you to work with Csound in realtime. It allows for 
    generating score with SoundObjects and working with MIDI keyboard input to 
    create notes and run with Csound instruments defined in your project. 
    Note: Blue Live works when using the Csound API, or on non-Windows 
    platforms when not using the Csound API. Windows does not allow piping 
    text to executable in a non-blocking way and therefore limits what can be 
    done when not using the API.
  </para>


  <section>
    <title>Motivation</title>

    <para>
      The motivation of Blue Live is primarily to aid the composer in working 
      out ideas and to help configure instrument, effects, and mixer settings. 
      You may find it helpful early on within the life a composition, when you 
      want to try out a number of different ideas in realtime. You may tweak 
      instrument parameters, mixer settings, try out different notes and chords 
      with a MIDI keyboard, and even work with different SoundObjects. Later, 
      when you have some ideas worked out, you can take your SoundObjects from 
      BlueLive into your score timeline and continue working from there.
    </para>
    <para>
      Beyond this primary capacity as a mode to aid composition, Blue Live has 
      some capacity to be used for realtime performance. The focus of Blue 
      Live's development is as a compositional aid first, and performance 
      second, though work continues to expand its usefulness in both regards.
    </para>

  </section>


  <section>
    <title>Working with Blue Live</title>

    <para>
      Blue Live is designed to work with the rest of your Blue project file. 
      When Blue Live is turned on, the Blue project generates everything from 
      the project except for the Score generated from the Score timeline. The 
      Global Score text will be used, but instead of &lt;TOTAL_DUR&gt; being 
      calculated from the score timeline, a default value of 3600 is used. This 
      allows your notes that would be used for effects instruments to run for 
      3600 seconds (this size can be modified; please make a request if 
      desired).
    </para>
    
    <para>
      The main toolbar has four buttons for Blue Live:
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      
      <varlistentry>
        <term>BlueLive</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Toggle button that stops and starts BlueLive</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Recompile</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>If BlueLive is running, this button will cause Blue to 
            recompile the CSD from your project and restart BlueLive.
            This is useful if you modify your orchestra code and want to quickly
            recompile and continue working with BlueLive.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      
      <varlistentry>
        <term>All Notes Off</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Turns off any score notes that are actively playing</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      
      <varlistentry>
        <term>MIDI Input</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Toggle button that turns on and off the configured MIDI devices
            setup in Program Options (discussed further below).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      
    </variablelist>

  <para>
    The primary Blue Live window is available from the Window Menu, or by using the
    ctrl-8 shortcut. The Blue Live window has three main tabs: the Live Space,
    the SCO Pad, and Options. These will be discussed int he following sections.
  </para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Live Space</title>

    <para>
      The Live Space is an area to work with SoundObjects. It is a table divided 
      into bins and rows of spaces to place SoundObjects. SoundObjects can be 
      copied to/from the Score Timeline as well as the Live Space. SoundObjects 
      can also be created within the Live Space by right clicking an empty bin 
      within the bins and choosing "Add SoundObject" from the popup menu. 
      Clicking on an occupied bin will select that SoundObject. The properties 
      for the SoundObject can be modified using the SoundObject Properties 
      Window, and the contents of the SoundObject can be modified from the 
      SoundObject Editor Window. Besides the selected and unselected states, 
      you can double-click a soundObject to put it into an enabled state. 
      Enabled objects are highlighted in orange and are the SoundObjects that 
      are triggered when multi-trigger or repeat is used.
    </para>
    
    <para>Once a SoundObject is added to the Live Space, it can be triggered 
      in one of two ways:
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Single Trigger</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Trigger the contents of the currently selected SoundObject. 
            This is done by using the keyboard shortcut ctrl-T (cmd-T on OSX).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Multi Trigger</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Triggers the contents of the currently enabled SoundObjects. 
            This is done either by using the Trigger button, or using the 
            keyboard shortcut ctrl-shift-T (cmd-shift-T on OSX).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      
    </variablelist>

    <para>
      Triggering a soundObject will take the score generated from it and pass 
      it immediately to the active Csound instance for BlueLive (BlueLive must
      be running for this to work). Scores are always generated with Time
      Behavior of None, processed through their NoteProcessors, then scaled 
      according to the given tempo.
    </para>
    <para>
      One can turn on Repeat to cause repeated trigger of enabled SoundObjects 
      according to the tempo given and the number of beats in which to 
      retrigger. For example, using a repeat of 4 means it will re-trigger 
      every four beats. The score is processed as mentioned above, but there 
      is no truncation done. Therefore, if a SoundObject generates a score of 
      8 beats, and there is a repeat of 4 beats, when the repeat occurs, there 
      will be 4 beats of overlap between the first trigger and the second 
      trigger.
    </para>
    <para>
      When Repeat is on, it will always finish out the current number of beats
      in the repeat at the current tempo, before applying any changes to tempo 
      and repeat. Modifyications to tempo and repeat will apply then on the next 
      repeat trigger.
    </para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Live Code</title>

    <para>
      The live coding tab holds Csound Orchestra code for live coding. Once
      BlueLive is enabled, you can select code within the Live Code tab and use
      the "ctrl-e" (cmd-e on OSX) shortcut to evaluate the code in the running
      Csound instance.  
    </para>

    <note>
      <title>Note</title>
      <para>When rendering for BlueLive, Blue will define a BLUE_LIVE orchestra
        and score macro.  This allows you to write conditional code (e.g., in
        the Global Orchestra or Global Score tabs for your project) that will
        run only when BLUE_LIVE is defined. (This can be checked using
        #ifdef's.)</para>
    </note>
  </section>



  <section>
    <title>SCO Pad</title>

    <note>
      <title>Note</title>
      <para>This feature will likely be removed in a future release.</para>
    </note>

    <para>
      This is an experimental feature to record MIDI input in a manner similar to
      to notation programs (press keys, then press 4 for a quarter note, 8 for
      and 8th note, etc.).  This feature requires MIDI Input to be turned on.
      This feature is experimental at this time.
    </para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Options</title>

    <para>
      The options panel allows setting up parameters for Blue Live. Currently it
      contains options for modifying the commandline string used when running
      BlueLive.  For most users, these modification will not be necessary and the
      default commandline used will be sufficient.
    </para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Working with MIDI</title>

    <para>Blue's MIDI system, when enabled, will listen to configured MIDI
      devices for notes, map the key and velocity, and generate Csound notes to
      achieve MIDI-like note-on and note-off type behavior. This allows working
      with a MIDI keyboard in realtime with your project instruments without
      modifying your instruments specifically for MIDI. This also means that when
      Blue's MIDI system is enabled, Csound MIDI processing should be disabled for
      your project.
    </para>

    <para>
      To configure what MIDI devices to use, go to the program Options settings
      (on OSX it is the application's Preferences, on other platofrms it is the
      Options menu item in the Tools menu) and under "Blue", go to MIDI.  There
      you will see a list of MIDI devices connected to your computer.  If you
      connected a device after starting Blue, you can rescan to find your MIDI
      device.  In this window you will configure what MIDI devices you want to
      use with Blue, but these devices will not be opened for listening until
      you enable MIDI Input on the BlueLive toolbar in the main application.
    </para>

    <para>
      Once you have configured what devices to use with Blue, return to the main
      program and enable MIDI input using the "MIDI Input" button, then start
      BlueLive.  At this point, when MIDI notes are played, Blue will take the
      incoming note data, map it according to the values configured in the
      MIDI Input Panel window (available from the Windows Menu), and then
      generate notes and pass them to Csound.
    </para>

    <para>
      For a MIDI note on, Blue will the channel number of the note and map it to the
      instrument in the orchestra manager by index.  For example, if you have
      three instruments numbered 1, 3, and 5, notes for MIDI channel 1 will
      generate with instr 1, notes for MIDI channel 2 will generate with
      instr 3, and notes for MIDI channel 3 will generate with instr 5.
    </para>

    <para>
      The MIDI key number as well as the velocity will be mapped according to
      the settings set in the MIDI Input Panel window.  This allows for generating
      frequency, Csound PCH, and using Scala Tuning files to generate either
      frequencies or BluePCH format text, amongst other values. 
    </para>

    <para>
      Instruments that are intended to be used with Blue's MIDI system will have
      to work with a 5 p-field note format.  This does not mean your instrument
      can only work with 5 p-fields, but rather that your instrument must support
      at least that.  An example Blue project can be found in
      examples/features/blueLiveMidi.blue (if you are using the OSX application,
      you may need to explore the contents of the Blue.app program to find the
      examples folder).
    </para>

  </section>



  <section>
    <title>Exploring Ideas</title>

    <para>
      Blue Live uses a subset of the same soundObjects that are available on the
      score timeline within the main editing window of Blue. Some possible ways
      you could explore ideas are:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>Trying out SCO ideas with GenericScore</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Testing your python functions with the PythonObject</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Testing your javaScript functions with the JavaScriptOObject</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          Using Cmask, nGen, Common Music, and other programs with the external
          soundObject to try out things live
        </para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

  </section>


</section>
