<section id="globalsManager">
    <title>Globals Manager</title>

<para>
  Csound Orchestra and Score text can be passed directly into a generated CSD
  by using the Global Orchestra and Global Score windows.
</para>

<simplesect>
<title>Global Orchestra</title>
       
<para>Anything here will be inserted into the &lt;CsOrchestra&gt; section of the
.CSD file before anything generated by the Orchestra. Things like global
variables, macros, or GUI instrument definitions may go here.</para>

</simplesect>


<simplesect>
<title>Global Score</title> 
       
<para>
  Anything here will be inserted into &lt;CsScore&gt; section of the .CSD file 
  before anything generated by the score timeline. the global score's processing
  is done outside of the score timelines, so any notes put here are not factored 
  into values calculated from the timeline, like total duration, nor are any 
  notes in the global score section translated like the timeline is when a 
  different start time is used other than 0.0. for instance, if you use 2.0 as a 
  start time, a note in the score timeline at 2.0 will be translated to start at 
  0.0, while a note with a start time of 2.0 in the global score section is not 
  affected and will start at time 2.0.
</para>

<para>There are also certain variables made available from Blue (Blue variables)
that are useful for specific purposes. One of them is &lt;TOTAL_DUR&gt;. An
example of its use is:</para>
         
<programlisting>i20 0 [&lt;TOTAL_DUR&gt; + 10] .95 1 1000</programlisting>        
         
<para>The note given above is for a global effect(a global reverb unit). This
note will always start at time zero regardless of when the score starts, and 
  will always last as long as the duration of the generated score from
the timeline plus 10 seconds. Because Blue variables are a text swap, the above
use of the bracket notation that Csound uses was necessary. For a score with a
20 second duration, the above note would have been generated as:</para> 
         
<programlisting>i20 0 [20 + 10] .95 1 1000</programlisting>

<para>Because of the Blue variable used, the note will correclty play regardless
  of when the score starts. If the the Blue variable was note used and was put 
  as a note in the Score timeline, the reverb may not run.</para>

<note>
  <title>Note</title>
  <para>When Blue variables were created, Blue did not have a Mixer system 
    implemented.  The above system continues to function, the practice of using
    the Mixer is highly recommended. This feature is left in for legacy 
    projects.
  </para>
</note>

</simplesect>

</section>
