<section id="blueSynthBuilder">
<title>BlueSynthBuilder</title>

<para>BlueSynthBuilder (BSB) allows the user to graphically build instrument
interfaces for their Csound instruments. The graphical interface is designed for
the use of exploring configuration of an instrument as well as adjustment to values 
in realtime(requires enabling using the Csound API, see 
<link linkend="csoundAPI">here</link>.</para>


<!-- ABOUT BSB -->

<section>
<title>About BlueSynthBuilder</title>

<simplesect>
<title>Principle of Design</title>

<para>It has been my experience that most Csound instruments tend to be limited
in user configurability of parameters than commercial synthesizer counterparts.
It is my belief that a large part of that is due to the text-based nature of
instruments. I've found that:</para>

<itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
        <para>Modular instruments are easier to express connections of modules 
        via text or code rather than visual paradigms (patch cables, line 
        connections), and thus easier to create the instrument by text</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
        <para>Graphical elements, however, excel in relaying information about 
        the configuration of the instrument to the user and also invite	    
        experimentation, while text-based configuration of instruments is often	   
        more difficult to quickly understand the parameters settings and 
        limits</para>
    </listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>Going completely graphical for the building of instruments, in the case of
systems like Max/PD/jMax or Reaktor, I've found that the instrument's design no
longer become apparent when viewing complicated patches. On the other hand,
using completely textual systems such as Csound or C++ coding, the design of the
instrument has a degree of transparency, while the configuration of the
parameters of the instrument becomes difficult to understand and invites less
exploration.</para></simplesect>

<simplesect>
<title>Hybrid Design</title>
<para>Using systems like MacCsound's widgets or blue's BlueSynthBuilder, one is
able to use graphical elements where they excel, in showing configuration of an
instrument and for manipulation of values, while using textual elements where 
they excel, in the design of instruments and expressing the connections between 
modules.</para>

<para>I have found that this sort of hybrid design offers the best of both worlds
and when I am spending time building and using new instruments, I can quickly
design an instrument and also explore the parameters of an instrument's design
by using blueSynthBuilder.</para>

</simplesect>

</section>

<!-- USING BSB -->

<section>
<title>Using BlueSynthBuilder</title>

<para>BlueSynthBuilder is divided up into two tabs, each of which handles the
different concerns of the instrument builder. Also, the process of creating
instruments and using instruments is also split between <emphasis>edit
</emphasis>and <emphasis>usage</emphasis> modes. Instrument builders will tend
to use both modes, while users of BSB instruments may not ever have to touch a
line of Csound instrument code or have to modify the instrument's UI at all
(though that liberty to do so is there). </para>

<section>
<title>Interface Editor</title>

<para>The Interface editor has two modes:</para>

<simplesect>
<title>Edit Mode</title>

<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject> <imagedata fileref="images/bsb_interface_edit.png" format="PNG" /> </imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>

<para>The user can add interface elements and modify their properties using the
property sheet on the right. To enable edit mode, click on the &quot;Edit
Enabled&quot; checkbox in the upper right of the BSB instrument editor. </para>

<para>Once the edit mode is enabled, right clicking in the main panel will show
a popup menu of available UI widgets for your instrument. After selecting and
inserting a widget, clicking on the widget will hilight it and show it's
properties in the property editor. You can also then drag the widget around to
place as you desire. </para>

<para>You may select multiple widgets by shift-clicking them, or by clicking on
an empty part of the edit panel and dragging a marquee to select a group of
widgets. After selecting multiple widgets, you can drag them around as a group,
as well as use the alignment and distribution options found on the right side
bottom to tidy up the UI.</para>

</simplesect>

<simplesect>
<title>Usage Mode</title>

<screenshot>
<!-- <screeninfo>BSB Interface in Usage Mode</screeninfo> -->
<mediaobject>
<imageobject> <imagedata fileref="images/bsb_interface_use.png" format="PNG" /> </imageobject>
<!-- <textobject> <phrase>BSB Interface in Usage Mode</phrase> </textobject>
<caption>
<para>BSB Interface in Usage Mode</para>
</caption> -->
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>

<para>Once in usage mode, users can configure the instrument by working with the
UI widgets: rotating knobs, moving sliders, etc. The values of the different UI
widgets will be reflected in the generated Csound instrument and will affect
the values in realtime if using the Csound API.</para>

</simplesect>


<section>
<title>Code Editor</title>

<para>The code editor is where the Csound instrument code is to be written. To
use the values from the widgets, use the replacement key of the widget within &lt;
&gt;'s, and that value will be replaced when the instrument is generated (the
replacement key is usually the objectName of the object; see table below).
</para>

<para>For example, if there's a knob with an objectName of
<emphasis>amplitude</emphasis> and the value is set to 0.5, the following
instrument code:</para>

<!--<example>
<title>BSB Code Input</title>-->
<programlisting>
iamp    = &lt;amplitude&gt; * 0dbfs
aout    vco2 iamp, 440

        outs aout, aout
</programlisting>
<!-- </example> -->

<para>will generate the following instrument:</para>

<!--<example>
<title>BSB Code Output</title> -->
<programlisting>
iamp    = 0.5 * 0dbfs

aout    vco2 iamp, 440

	    outs aout, aout
</programlisting>
<!-- </example> -->

<para> For convenience, a replacement key code completion popup has been added.
When editing code
press ctrl-shift-space and a popup dialog will appear with a list of all the
replacement keys that have been assigned to interface objects. Selecting a
replacement key will insert that key into the code text area, already formatted
within &lt; and &gt;.</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Widget Values</title>

<para>The following lists what values the widgets will emit when generating
instruments:</para>

<table>
<title>Widget Values</title>
    <tgroup cols="3">
    <thead>
        <row><entry>Widget</entry><entry>Replacement Key</entry><entry>Value</entry></row>
    </thead>

    <tbody>
        <row>
            <entry>Knob</entry>
            <entry>objectName</entry>
            <entry>float value from knob</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>Horizontal Slider</entry>
            <entry>objectName</entry>
            <entry>float value from slider</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>Horizontal Slider Bank</entry>
            <entry>objectName_sliderNum (for each slider)</entry>
            <entry>float value from slider</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>Vertical Slider</entry>
            <entry>objectName</entry>
            <entry>float value from slider</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>Vertical Slider Bank</entry>
            <entry>objectName_sliderNum (for each slider)</entry>
            <entry>float value from slider</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>Label</entry>
            <entry>none</entry>
            <entry>none</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>Checkbox</entry>
            <entry>objectName</entry>
            <entry>1 or 0, depending on if checked or not</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>Dropdown List</entry>
            <entry>objectName</entry>
            <entry>Generates index of selected item when item is made 
              automatable, or uses value from user-assigned Dropdown List
            </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>SubChannel Dropdown List</entry>
            <entry>objectName</entry>
            <entry>
              Value from Dropdown List that is a named subchannel from the blue
              Mixer
            </entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>XY Controller</entry>
            <entry>objectNameX, objectNameY</entry>
            <entry>X and Y value</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>LineObject</entry>
            <entry>objectName_lineName (for each line)</entry>
            <entry>list of values from line (can be comma separated,
            with or without leading 0.0 X value, and x values can be
            generated either in absolute or relative terms)</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>Text Field</entry>
            <entry>objectName</entry>
            <entry>Value from text field (compile-time only).</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
            <entry>File Selector</entry>
            <entry>objectName</entry>
            <entry>If stringChannelEnabled is selected, outputs a Csound string 
              variable (S-var) that can be updated at runtime if API is enabled, 
              if stringChannelEnabled is set to off, outputs as a string 
              (without quotes) at compilation time
            </entry>
        </row>
    </tbody>
    </tgroup>
</table>

<simplesect>
<title>NOTES</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>

        <para>For the Label object, you are able to style the label by using
        HTML. To use this feature, when setting the text of the label, enter the
        HTML label within &lt;html&gt; tags, such as "&lt;html&gt;&lt;font
        size="+1"&gt;My Label&lt;/font&gt;&lt;/html&gt;".</para>

      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
</simplesect>

</section>

</section>

<section>
<title>Presets</title>

<para>Since 0.95.0, BlueSynthBuilder now has the capability to save and load
presets. These presets are for usage-time and not design-time, and they save a
snapshot of all of the values for the widgets. They do not save x/y coordinates
or other configuration for the widget, only the value. </para>

<para>You can add presets and folders of presets using the presets menu in the
upper left of the BSB editor. Each menu has an option for adding a folder or
adding a preset to it. You can also manage presets by using the "Manage Presets"
button. This will open up a dialog with a tree view of your presets, allowing
you to rename the presets and folders, as well as reorganize by dragging and
dropping. You can remove presets and folders here by right-clicking and
selecting the remove option. Changes in the dialog are not committed until you
press the save button, so if you close the window or cancel, you're old settings
will be still in tact.</para>

</section>

<section id="bsbAutomation">
<title>Automation</title>

<para>
blue supports automation of BSB Widget values for those which support 
automation.  For these widgets, automation must be enabled before they allowed
to be automated.  When making them automatable, the place in Csound instrument
code where the widget value will be added to the generated Csound code must be
a place where a k-rate signal is allowed, otherwise the code will not compile
and Csound will not run the project.  This is required because when using 
the Csound API, the signal will need to be k-rate to allow for live 
modification of the value when rendering.</para>

<para>More information on paramenter automation can be found 
<link linkend="parameterAutomation">here</link>.
       
</para>

<note>
<title>Note</title>

<para>In 0.124.3, a change was made that breaks backwards compatibility. 
Previously, if a BSBObject was set to have "Automation Allowed" but was not 
itself automated, it would compile as a constant in the generated CSD.  As of 
0.124.3, if a widget is made to allow automation, the Csound code that uses the 
widget value must accept a k-rate signal, whether the API is used or not.</para>

<para>If you have a project that rendered fine before 0.124.3 but afterwards 
can not render due to problems with Csound complaining that "k-rate signals not
allowed", then you will need to either set the widget to not allow automation or
change the Csound code so that it will work with the generated k-rate signal.
</para>
</note>
    
</section>

<section id="bsbWidgetRandomization">
<title>Randomization</title>

<para>Since 0.117.0, users are able to randomize values for widgets in a 
BlueSynthBuilder instrument.  To use, first choose which widgets are set to be
randomized in edit mode, then in usage mode, right click on the panel in an area
not covered by a widget, then select "Randomize" from the popup menu.  The 
following widgets are cable of being randomized:</para>

 <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Knob</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Horizontal Slider</para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para>Vertical Slider</para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para>Horizontal Slider Bank</para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para>Vertical Slider Bank</para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para>XY Controller</para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para>Checkbox</para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para>Dropdown List</para>
      </listitem>
      
    </itemizedlist>

</section>

</section>

</section>