<section id="timewarpProcessor">
<title>Time Warp Processor</title>
         
<para>parameters: TimeWarpString</para>
         
<para>Warps time in the same way as Csound t-statement, but does not require "t"
to be used. Statements are in alternating pairs of beat number and tempo.</para>

<para>From the Csound Manual:</para>

<para>Time and Tempo-for-that-time are given as ordered couples that define
points on a "tempo vs. time" graph. (The time-axis here is in beats so is not
necessarily linear.) The beat-rate of a Section can be thought of as a movement
from point to point on that graph: motion between two points of equal height
signifies constant tempo, while motion between two points of unequal height will
cause an accelarando or ritardando accordingly. The graph can contain
discontinuities: two points given equal times but different tempi will cause an
immediate tempo change.</para>

<para> Motion between different tempos over non-zero time is inverse linear.
That is, an accelerando between two tempos M1 and M2 proceeds by linear
interpolation of the single-beat durations from 60/M1 to 60/M2.</para>

<para>The first tempo given must be for beat 0. 
</para>
     
<simplesect>
<title>Notes on Usage</title>

<itemizedlist>
 
    <listitem>
    
        <para>Beat values for beat/tempo pairs should related to the score
        *before* any time behavior is applied. For example, for the following
        score:</para>
    
<programlisting>
i1 0 1 2 3 4
i1 1 1 3 4 5 
i1 2 1 3 4 5 
i1 3 1 3 4 5 
</programlisting>
    
        <para>if it is in a GenericScore soundObject of duration 20, if you want
        the tempo to decrease in half by the last note, you would enter a value
        for the processor as "0 60 3 30" and not "0 60 20 30"</para>
    
    </listitem>
    
  <listitem><para>If you're using a time behavior of "Repeat", remember that
  time behavior is applied *after* noteProcessors, and the resulting score will
  be a time warped score repeated x times and *NOT* a score repeated x time and
  then timewarped</para></listitem>
    
  <listitem><para>Time Warping, when used with a time behavior of "Scale", be
  aware that estimating the final tempo of the object may be tricky, as the
  scaling will alter the duration of notes</para></listitem>
    
</itemizedlist> 

</simplesect>

</section>