<section id="blueLive">
  <title>Blue Live</title>

  <screenshot>
    <screeninfo>Blue Live</screeninfo>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/blueLive.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>Blue Live</phrase>
      </textobject>
      <caption>
        <para>Blue Live</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>

  <para>
    Blue Live allows you to work with Csound in realtime. It allows for generating
    score with SoundObjects and working with MIDI keyboard input to create notes
    and run with Csound instruments defined in your project. Note: Blue Live
    works when using the Csound API, or on non-Windows platforms when not using
    the Csound API. Windows does not allow piping text to executable in a
    non-blocking way and therefore limits what can be done when not using the
    API.
  </para>


  <section>
    <title>Motivation</title>

    <para>
      The motivation of Blue Live is primarily to aid the composer in working out
      ideas and to help configure instrument, effects, and mixer settings. You
      may find it helpful early on within the life a composition, when you
      want to try out a number of different ideas in realtime.  You may tweak
      instrument parameters, mixer settings, try out different notes and chords
      with a MIDI keyboard, and even work with different SoundObjects.
      Later, when you have some ideas worked out, you can take your SoundObjects
      from blueLive into your score timeline and continue working from there.
    </para>
    
    <para>
      Beyond this primary capacity as a mode to aid composition, Blue Live has
      some capacity to be used for realtime performance.  Though this isn't it's
      primary aim at this time (as of version 2.1.0), it can certainly be used
      in this regard.  For now, however, the role of Blue Live is primarily one
      of aiding the compositional process.  More full realtime performance 
      capabilities will be introduced as development scheduling allows.
    </para>

  </section>


  <section>
    <title>Working with Blue Live</title>

    <para>
      Blue Live is designed to work with the rest of your blue project file. All
      aspects of your regular blue file that would normally be written out to a
      CSD file are done so
      <emphasis>except</emphasis>
      SCO text that would be generated from the score timeline. The global score
      are will be written out, but instead of &lt;TOTAL_DUR&gt; being calculated
      from the score timeline, a default value of 3600 is used. This allows your
      notes that would be used for effects instruments to run for 3600 seconds
      (this size can be modified; please make a request if desired).
    </para>
    
    <para>
      The main toolbar has four buttons for blue Live: "blueLive" (which starts
      and stops blueLive), "Recompile" (which regenerates the CSD from your project
      and restarts blueLive, useful if you modified your orchestra code),
      "All Notes Off" (turns off any score notes that are actively playing), and
      "MIDI Input" (turns on and off the configured MIDI devices setup in the
      program's options, discussed further below). 
    </para>

    <para>
      The primary Blue Live window is available from the Window Menu, or by using the
      ctrl-8 shortcut. The Blue Live window has three main tabs: the Live Space,
      the SCO Pad, and Options. These will be discussed below.
    </para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Live Space</title>

    <para>
      The Live Space is an area to work with SoundObjects.  SoundObjects can be
      copied to/from the Score Timeline as well as the Live Space. SoundObjects
      can also be created within the Live Space by using the "+" button. Once a
      SoundObject is added to the Live Space, it can be triggered by hitting the
      trigger button for that SoundObject row in the table.  Triggering a
      soundObject will take the score generated from it and pass it immediately
      to the active Csound instance for blueLive (blueLive must be running for
      this to work).  You can edit the properties for a Live Space soundObject
      by select it in the Live Space table, then using the normal SoundObject
      Editor window and SoundObject Properties Window to modify settings.
    </para>

    <para>
      When using the Live Space, you can copy objects from the timeline, then by
      right-clicking in the Live Space, use the popup menu to paste the copied
      soundObject into the Live Space. You can then make changes to Live Space
      objects and try out the different ideas in realtime.  After changes have
      been made, you can copy the soundObject using the right-click popup menu
      and paste it back into the score timeline.
    </para>

    <para>
      NOTE: All objects are set to generate as if their time behavior was set to none,
      meaning no scaling or repetition is done.
    </para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>SCO Pad</title>

    

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Options</title>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Working with MIDI</title>

    <para>blue's MIDI system, when enabled, will listen to configured MIDI
    devices for notes, map the key and velocity, and generate Csound notes to
    achieve MIDI-like note-on and note-off type behavior. This allows working
    with a MIDI keyboard in realtime with your project instruments without
    modifying your instruments specifically for MIDI. This also means that when
    blue's MIDI system is enabled, Csound MIDI processing should be disabled for
    your project.</para>

    <para>
      To configure what MIDI devices to use, go to the program Options settings
      (on OSX it is the application's Preferences, on other platofrms it is the
      Options menu item in the Tools menu) and under "blue", go to MIDI.  There
      you will see a list of MIDI devices connected to your computer.  If you
      connected a device after starting blue, you can rescan to find your MIDI
      device.  In this window you will configure what MIDI devices you want to
      use with blue, but these devices will not be opened for listening until
      you enable MIDI Input on the blueLive toolbar in the main application.
    </para>

    <para>
      Once you have configured what devices to use with blue, return to the main
      program and enable MIDI input using the "MIDI Input" button, then start
      blueLive.  At this point, when MIDI notes are played, blue will take the
      incoming note data, map it according to the values configured in the
      MIDI Input Panel window (available from the Windows Menu), and then
      generate notes and pass them to Csound.
    </para>

    <para>
      For a MIDI note on, blue will the channel number of the note and map it to the
      instrument in the orchestra manager by index.  For example, if you have
      three instruments numbered 1, 3, and 5, notes for MIDI channel 1 will
      generate with instr 1, notes for MIDI channel 2 will generate with
      instr 3, and notes for MIDI channel 3 will generate with instr 5.
    </para>


  </section>



  <section>
    <title>EXPLORING IDEAS</title>

    <para>
      Blue Live uses a subset of the same soundObjects that are available on the
      score timeline within the main editing window of blue. Some possible ways
      you could explore ideas are:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>trying out SCO ideas with genericScore</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>testing your python functions with the pythonObject</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>testing your javaScript functions with the rhinoObject</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          using Cmask, nGen, Common Music, and other programs with the external
          soundObject to try out things live
        </para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

  </section>


</section>
