<section id="blueLive">
  <title>Blue Live</title>

  <screenshot>
    <screeninfo>Blue Live</screeninfo>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/blueLive.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>Blue Live</phrase>
      </textobject>
      <caption>
        <para>Blue Live</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>

  <para>
    The Blue Live dialog allows you to test ideas and perform in realtime with
    Commandline Csound via the -L stdin line events mechanism (not all versions
    of Csound are capable of supporting this feature, particularly all Windows
    versions; please check with the version of Csound you are using to find out 
    if it supports this).  Blue Live will work with any version of Csound when
    using the Csound API.
  </para>


  <simplesect>
    <title>Motivation</title>

    <para>
      The motivation of Blue Live is that I wanted to be able to test ideas with
      the instruments of my current work file and do so in a way that would be
      easy for me to take my tests and put them in to use for composition. One
      possible solution to my problem could be to make instruments my
      instruments multipurposed as to be triggerable by MIDI and SCO. That way I
      could play the instruments in realtime via MIDI and then, having found
      some ideas I liked, start working in SCO.
    </para>

    <para>
      However, in working out ideas this way I would still have to spend time to
      notate in SCO the ideas I was working out in MIDI. Also, I found working
      out ideas on the note level to be hard to work out with MIDI controllers.
      (The flipside was also true, though, and working on the level of the sound
      would sometimes be better off by using MIDI than using SCO.)
    </para>

    <para>
      Blue Live solved my compositional problems by letting me test out ideas
      with writing SCO and using them in realtime. That way, after working with
      the ideas, I could directly transfer the ideas to my score timeline and
      work with them in the context of the piece at hand.
    </para>

    <para>
      Also, I found I enjoyed performing with Blue Live, as I found it a
      comfortable level of abstraction to work with.
    </para>

  </simplesect>


  <simplesect>
    <title>Working with Blue Live</title>

    <para>
      Blue Live is designed to work with the rest of your blue project file. All
      aspects of your regular blue file that would normally be written out to a
      CSD file are done so
      <emphasis>except</emphasis>
      SCO text that would be generated from the score timeline. The global score
      are will be written out, but instead of &lt;TOTAL_DUR&gt; being calculated
      from the score timeline, a default value of 3600 is used. This allows your
      notes that would be used for effects instruments to run for 3600 seconds
      (this size can be altered if anyone needs be; just email me a request).
    </para>

    <para>
      So in the Blue Live dialog, you'll see a textfield for a commandline at
      the top, a start/stop button, an area to add/remove soundObjects, and an
      area for the editors of those soundObjects.
    </para>

    <para>
      The commandline is the Csound command you'll use to run Csound with the
      temp CSD file that is generated. This command must have "-L stdin" as part
      of its arguments for Csound to expect SCO input from stdin, which blue
      uses to send SCO text to Csound. The default command of "csound -Wdo
      devaudio -L stdin" should work as a basic start.
    </para>

    <para>
      The start/stop button will start Csound using the user-given commandline
      and will run it with a temporary CSD file generated from the blue project
      file (minus the SCO from the score timeline). If already running, the
      button will stop the previous performance. Also, if you close the dialog
      while Csound is running, the dialog will stop the performance.
    </para>

    <para>
      The main black window holds your soundObjects. Right-Clicking in the main
      area will bring up a dialog for adding soundObjects. The soundObject GUI's
      that are added when adding soundObjects in this area consist of a large
      trigger button that will generate notes from the soundObject and pass it
      to Csound via stdin, as well as a label. Clicking the label once will
      bring up the soundObject's editor in the bottom part of the window.
      Double-Clicking the label will allow you to edit the name of the
      soundObject.
    </para>

  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title>EXPLORING IDEAS</title>

    <para>
      Blue Live uses a subset of the same soundObjects that are available on the
      score timeline within the main editing window of blue. Some possible ways
      you could explore ideas are:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>trying out SCO ideas with genericScore</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>testing your python functions with the pythonObject</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>testing your javaScript functions with the rhinoObject</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          using Cmask, nGen, Common Music, and other programs with the external
          soundObject to try out things live
        </para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title>Other Things to Note</title>

    <para>
      All objects are set to generate as if their time behavior was set to none,
      meaning no scaling or repetition is done
    </para>

  </simplesect>

</section>
