<section id="importMIDI">
  <title>Importing MIDI Files</title>

  <para>
    Blue is able to import MIDI files and set up a Blue project file from the
    note information in the MIDI file, using the settings given by the user. To
    import a MIDI file, choose the "Import MIDI File" option from the File menu.
    Next, using the file dialog to locate the MIDI file to import. After
    selecting the desired file, Blue will show the following MIDI Import
    Settings dialog for you to configure how you would like to import the MIDI
    note information. (Note: Blue will only show information for tracks where
    note data was found.)
  </para>

  <screenshot>
    <screeninfo>MIDI Import Settings</screeninfo>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/midiImportSettings.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>MIDI Import Settings</phrase>
      </textobject>
      <caption>
        <para>MIDI Import Settings</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>

  <para>The table column information is as follows:</para>

  <variablelist>
    <title>MIDI Import Settings</title>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Track</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The original MIDI track number to which this setting is to be applied
          to. This column is not editable is for reference purpose only.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Instrument ID</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The Csound instrument ID to use for this track. This will replace the
          &lt;INSTR_ID&gt; key within the note template. This value is treated
          as a string to allow users to assign the track information to Csound
          named instruments. If one is doing so, one must quote the name, i.e.
          use "trumpet" instead of trumpet (without quotes), otherwise the
          output will not be legal Csound SCO. Default value is the number of
          the MIDI track.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Note Template</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Template note text to use for generating Csound SCO from the MIDI
          data. The default note template is "i&lt;INSTR_ID&gt; &lt;START&gt;
          &lt;DUR&gt; &lt;KEY&gt; &lt;VELOCITY&gt;". By having note templates,
          the user can massage the note information to work with any number of
          pfields that their instruments require.
        </para>

        <para>The following values are allowed in the note template:</para>

        <table>
          <title>Key Values</title>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>Shortcuts</entry>
                <entry>Description</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>

            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>&lt;INSTR_ID&gt;</entry>
                <entry>The instrument ID assigned in the track settings.</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>&lt;START&gt;</entry>
                <entry>Start Time of Note</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>&lt;DUR&gt;</entry>
                <entry>Duration of Note</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>&lt;KEY&gt;</entry>
                <entry>MIDI key number</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>&lt;KEY_PCH&gt;</entry>
                <entry>MIDI key number as Csound PCH</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>&lt;KEY_OCT&gt;</entry>
                <entry>MIDI key number as Csound OCT</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>&lt;KEY_CPS&gt;</entry>
                <entry>MIDI key number as CPS</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>&lt;VELOCITY&gt;</entry>
                <entry>MIDI velocity number</entry>
              </row>

              <row>
                <entry>&lt;VELOCITY_AMP&gt;</entry>
                <entry>MIDI velocity number as amplitude</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>

        <para>
          The button labelled "Reference" on the dialog will pop open the above
          information for quick reference of the allowable replacement keys for
          note templates.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
      <term>Trim Time</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          This option will shift the generated SoundObject to the time of the
          first note and then take the generated notes for the track and shift
          them all so that the first note starts at time 0 so that there is no
          empty time at the beginning of the track's note information.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

  </variablelist>

  <para>
    After finishing configuring settings for the imported MIDI data, Blue will
    generate the notes with one SoundLayer per MIDI track, and on each
    SoundLayer it will contain one GenericScore SoundObject containing the
    converted MIDI score.
  </para>

  <note>
    <title>Note</title>
    <para>
      The current implementation does not handle cases where there are
      overlapping notes of the same MIDI note number within the same track and
      results are unpredictable. Also, only MIDI files where time is PPQ is
      supported at the moment (non-SMPTE). Users wanting support for either of
      these cases or have other ideas they would like implemented are requested
      to make feature requests on the Blue mailing list or to use the help menu
      "Request a Feature" option.
    </para>
  </note>

</section>
