<section id="blueShare">
  <title>BlueShare</title>

  <screenshot>
    <screeninfo>BlueShare</screeninfo>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/blueShare.png" format="PNG" scalefit="1" 
                   width="100%" contentheight="100%" />
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>BlueShare</phrase>
      </textobject>
      <caption>
        <para>BlueShare</para>
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>

  <para>
    BlueShare is an online, in-program way to share instruments, effects, and 
    SoundObjects with other Blue users. BlueShare does not require a user account to download
    items, but does require one for uploading. If you would like to share an 
    instrument or effect, please sign up for an account at
    <ulink url="http://blue.kunstmusik.com">http://blue.kunstmusik.com</ulink>
  </para>
  
  <para>
    To use BlueShare, go to the Tools menu to open it up.  Blue will contact
    the server to get a list of Instrument, Effects, and SoundObjects
    available.  From there, you can browse categories, then select an item in
    the upper-right table to get more information. Once you find something you
    are interested to try, select "Import Instrument", "Import Effect", or
    "Import SoundObject". Blue will download the instrument, effect, or
    SoundObject into the User Instrument Library, Effects Library, or User
    SoundObject Library in a folder called "Imported Instruments", "Imported
    Effects", or "Import SoundObjects".
  </para>
  
  <para>
    To upload and instrument or effect, switch to the Export tab.  From there
    you will see a place to enter your username and password, a listing of
    instruments, effects, or SoundObjects from your libraries, a tree of
    categories to use for uploading, and a description box (pre-populated with
    the Comments field of your Instrument or Effect). You can then press the
    "Submit" button to send it to the server. 
  </para>

  <para>
    The manage tab allows you to pull down a list of your contributed
    instruments, effects, and SoundObjects.  You can then remove the item from
    BlueShare using "Remove" button.
  </para>

</section>
