<section id="commandBlocks">
  <title>Command Blocks</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>
      Command Blocks are Csound ORC code with special directions to blue on how
      to processes them. The are available to use only within the Global
      Orchestra areas of Instruments (not to be confused with the global
      orchestra area in the globals manager tab) and were created to help users
      build fully-encapsulated instruments, such that an instrument and all of
      its necessary parts could be grouped together. (For more information, see
      the <link linkend="createEncapsulatedInstrument">
      Create Encapsulated Instruments</link> section of the manual.)
    </para>

  </section>


  <section>
    <title>Basic Usage</title>

    <para>
      To use a command block, you will need to wrap the section of orc code that
      you want blue to process with the command in the following manner:

<screen>
;[command to use]{ 
...Csound Orchestra Code... 
;}
</screen>

    </para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Available Commands</title>

    <simplesect>
      <title>once</title>

      <para>

        Once blocks are useful to limit how many times a block of code will be
        generated in the final CSD and is more for efficiency than anything else
        (so Csound doesn't define the same ftable more than it has to, for
        example). An example of this:

<screen>
;[once]{ 
gaLeft init 0 gaRight init 0 
;}
</screen>

        In this case, if the above gaLeft and gaRight init statement, wrapped in
        a once block, is used in multiple instruments, then regardless it will
        be generated only once in the final CSD. So a use case for the above
        would be if you have all of your instruments output to the above global
        variables for extra processing by an always-on reverb, you would want to
        add the above to all of the instruments and also the reverb. Then, if
        you start a new project and may want to reuse a few of your instruments
        as well as the reverb, you can just copy them into your new project's
        orchestra and start working away, knowing your global variables will be
        initialized and ready to go.

      </para>

    </simplesect>

    <simplesect>
      <title>pre</title>

      <para>

        Pre blocks are useful if you need the enclosed ORC code to be generated
        before any other global orc code. When blue goes to process the project
        to generate a CSD file, it normally starts of the existing global
        orchestra code from the globals manager, then appends all global orc
        from instruments and soundObjects to it, one after the other. By using a
        pre block, the code enclosed will be pushed up to the top of the global
        orchestra of the CSD (instrument 0).
      </para>

      <para>
        The scenario which required a solution such as this was when working
        with the fluidSynth opcodes. For those set of opcodes, a fluidEngine
        needs to be initialized before loading of soundfonts into that engine.
        The design I had wanted was to have the instrument that did the
        fluidOutput also have the engine initialization. This was a problem
        because the fluidOutput needed to be placed at an instrument number
        higher than the fluidNote playing instruments for the output chain to
        work correctly. So here was a case of an instrument that needed to have
        its instrument generate later than the instruments that it depended on,
        but also have its own fluidEngine initialization happen before all the
        other soundFonts load in in their own global orc statements. The
        solution then was to create the once block feature and allow for
        targetting global orc code to be prepended to the top of the generated
        global orc code.

      </para>

    </simplesect>

  </section>

</section>

