<section id="rendering">
  <title>Rendering</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>
      blue offers a number of ways of rendering the project, each method useful
      for different purposes that the user may have. The following section
      explains the ways which blue is able to render a .blue project file as
      well as possible use-case scenarios to guide the user on how that feature
      may be useful.
    </para>

  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Render Methods</title>

    <simplesect>
      <title>Render in Real-Time</title>
      
      <para>
        Rendering in uses the project's Real-Time render settings to render the
        project in realtime to the users soundcard. This is the most common
        rendering one will likely use. To use this, you can press the play
        button at the top of the window, use the "Project-&gt;Render/Stop
        Project" menu option, or use the F9 shortcut key.

      </para>
      
    </simplesect>
      
    <simplesect>
      <title>Generate CSD to Screen</title>

      <para>
        blue's general method of communicating with Csound is by generating a
        CSD file and calling Csound to run it.  For debugging purposes, it is 
        often useful to see if what you think you are doing inside blue is 
        matching the generated CSD file.  You can generate the CSD to screen
        by using the "Project-&gt;Generate CSD to Screen" menu option, or by
        using the ctrl-shift-g shortcut.
      </para>
            
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect>
      <title>Generate CSD to Disk</title>
      
      <para>
        If you'd like to generate a CSD from the current project to a file, you
        can do so by using the "Project-&gt;Generate CSD to File" menu option,
        or by using the ctrl-g shortcut.
      </para>      
      
    </simplesect>

    <simplesect>
      <title>Render to Disk</title>
    
      <para>
        The Render to Disk option will use the project's Disk Render Options
        from its project properties to generate a soundfile on disk (format of
        file depends on how user configures commandline options). I've found
        this useful for rendering a wav to disk and converting to MP3 to listen
        to on the go so I can review my current work. To render to disk, you can
        do so by using the "File-&gt;Render to Disk" menu option or use the
        ctrl-shift-F9 shortcut.
      </para>
      
    </simplesect>
    
    <simplesect>
      <title>Render to Disk and Play</title>

      <para>
        The Render to Disk and play option will use the project's Disk Render
        Options from its project properties to generate a soundfile on disk and
        after finishing, play the generated file using blue's soundfile player,
        located in the SoundFile manager tab. This feature is useful if you're
        working on a piece that has processing demands beyond what your computer
        is capable of in realtime, so you can have it render to disk first and
        then play, which will give very smooth playback. It is also useful if
        you render in realtime with lower quality settings but use higher
        quality settings for final project output, as you can occasionally test
        what the output would be like using this feature. To use this option,
        you can use the "File-&gt;Render to Disk and Play" menu option or use
        the ctrl-F9 shortcut.
      </para>
      
    </simplesect>    
    
  </section>


</section>

