<section id="conceptsSoundObjects">
<title>SoundObjects</title>

<section>
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
	The concept of SoundObjects is the foundation of blue's design in organizing
	musical ideas.  This section will discuss what is a SoundObject, how this idea
	is implemented in blue, and strategies on how to use the concept of SoundObjects
	in organizing your own musical work.
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>What is a SoundObject?</title>

	<para>
		SoundObjects in blue represent a <emphasis> perceived
		sound idea, whether it be a single atomic sound event or aggregate of other
		sound objects</emphasis>. A SoundObject on the timeline can represent
		many things, whether it is a single sound, a melody, a rhythm, a phrase, a section
		involving phrases and multiple lines, a gesture, or anything else that is
		a perceived sound idea.
	</para>

	<para>
		Just as there are many ways to think about music, each with their own model
		for describing sound and vocabulary for explaining music, there are a number 
		of different SoundObjects in blue.  Each SoundObject in blue is useful for different
		purposes, with some being more appropriate for expressing certain musical ideas
		than others.  For example, using a scripting object like the PythonObject or 
		RhinoObject would service a user who is trying to express a musical idea that
		may require an algorithmic basis, while the PianoRoll would be useful for those
		interested in notating melodic and harmonic ideas. The variety of different
		SoundObjects allows for users to choose what tool will be the most appropriate
		to express their musical ideas.
	</para>
	
	<para>
		Since there are many ways to express musical ideas, to fully allow the range
		of expression that Csound offers, blue's SoundObjects are capable of
		generating different things that Csound will use.  Although most often 
		they are used mostly for generating Csound SCO text, SoundObjects may also 
		generate ftables, instruments, user-defined opcodes, and everything else 
		that would be needed to express a musical idea in Csound.  
	</para>
	
	<para>
		Beyond each SoundObject's unique capabilities, SoundObjects do share common
		qualities: name, start time, duration, end time.  Most will also support
		a Time Behavior (Scale, Repeat, or None) which affects how the notes generated
		by the SoundObject will be adjusted--if at all--to the duration of the SoundObject.
		Most will also support NoteProcessors, another key tool in Csound for manipulating
		notes generated from a SoundObject.  All SoundObjects also support a background
		color property, used strictly for visual purposes on the timeline.
	</para>	

</section>

</section>

