<section id="soundObjectLibrary">
  <title>SoundObject Library</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>
      The SoundObject Library is a place where one can store soundObjects from
      the timeline. The library can simply be a place to store a soundObject
      idea that the user may want to user later, but more importantly it allows
      for Instances of the soundObject to be made. Instances of soundObjects
      point to and soundObject in the library and when the instance is
      generating its score, it will actually call the soundObject in the library
      to generate its score and then apply it's own properties and
      noteProcessors to the generated score. Updating a soundObject in the
      library will then update all instances of that soundObject. This feature
      is useful to represent the idea of a motive, with instances of the motive
      allowing to have transformations by use of noteProcessors.
    </para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      The general pattern of usage for the SoundObject Library entails:

      <orderedlist>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Add SoundObject to the Library. This is done by selecting a
            soundObject, right-clicking the soundObject to open up the popup
            menu and selecting "Add to SoundObject Library". 
          </para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>
            After doing this, your soundObject will have been added to the
            library and the soundObject on the timeline will have been replaced
            with an Instance soundObject which will be pointing to the
            soundObject now in the library.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>
            At this point, the user can now take advantage of the library by 
            making copies of the instance object on the timeline and pasting in
            more instances.  These instances can be placed anywhere, have 
            different durations and time behaviors, as well as have their own
            individual noteProcessors.  This allows expressing ideas such as
            "This is an instance of the primary motive (soundObject in the 
            library) but transposed up a major 3rd, retrograded, and inverted", 
            or an idea like "I've got drum pattern A in the library and I have
            instances of it here and here and ...".
            
            <note>
              <title>Note</title>
              <para>
                When copying and pasting Instance soundObjects, they are all
                pointing to the soundObject in the library.
              </para>
            </note>
            
          </para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>
            You can also then make instances of soundObjects in the library by
            opening up the SoundObject Library dialog (available from the 
            Window menu or by using the F4 shortcut key).  There you have 
            the following options:
            
            <variablelist>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>Copy</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    This makes a copy of the selected SoundObject and puts it in
                    the buffer. This is a copy of the original soundObject and
                    not an Instance. After copying to the buffer, you can paste
                    as normal on the timeline.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Copy Instance</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    This makes a Instance of the selected SoundObject and puts
                    it in the buffer. This Instance will point to the original
                    soundObject. After copying to the buffer, you can paste as
                    normal on the timeline.
                  </para>

                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Remove</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    This will remove the selected SoundObject from the library.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
                                          
            </variablelist>
            
          </para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>You can also then edit the soundObject in the library from 
            within the SoundObject Library dialog by selecting the soundObject
            in the list.  The editor for the SoundObject will appear below.  
          
            <note>
              <title>Note</title>
              <para>
                Editing the SoundObject in the library will affect all instances of
                that SoundObject.
              </para>
            </note>
          
          </para>
          
        </listitem>

      </orderedlist>

    </para>

  </section>

</section>