<section id="installation">
  <title>Installation</title>

  <section id="requirements">
    <title>Requirements</title>

    <para>
      Blue requires Java 11 or greater JVM (Java Virtual 
      Machine) to be installed on your system, as well as Csound. Java 
      installations usually come in two flavors: a JRE (Java Runtime Environment)
      which contains just a JVM for running applications, and a JDK (Java Development
      Kit) which contains the JVM as well as development tools. Because Blue 
      comes with scripting tools that use JDK features, it is recommended to 
      install the full JDK, and not just the JRE.
    </para> 

    <para>
      To test to 
      see if you have a JVM installed and what version, at 
      a command prompt type "java -version". If you see something along the 
      lines of "command not found" then you need to install a Java Virtual 
      Machine. 
    </para>

    <para>If you do not have Java installed, the recommended JDK to install is 
      AdoptOpenJDK, available at:
    </para>

    <para>
        <ulink url="https://adoptopenjdk.net/">https://adoptopenjdk.net/</ulink>
    </para>

    <para>
      On this page, look for the download link for your platform. Be sure to choose 
      the version of JDK that matches your CPU type and Csound version (choose 64-bit if in doubt).
    </para>

  </section>

  <section id="installingBlue">
    <title>Installing Blue</title>

    <para>
      To install Blue, you should download the latest ZIP file from
      the Blue releases page
      <ulink url="https://github.com/kunstmusik/blue/releases">here</ulink>. 
      For macOS users, download the macOS zip file which contains Blue.app.  You can 
      double-click the Application to run, as well as copy it to your 
      Applications folder to install it.</para>

    <para> 
      For Linux and Windows users, download the appropriate zip file and unzip it.  Inside
      of the bin folder you will see a "blue" script for Linux or a
      "blue64.exe" file for use on Windows. (A 32-bit version, "blue.exe", is
      also included for those using an older version of Csound that is compiled
      for 32-bit Windows.)</para>

    <para>
      Note: After starting Blue, you may want to explore the example projects
      and pieces found in the Blue/example folder (or right-click and explore
      contents of Blue.app/example if on OSX).
    </para>

    <section id="platformNotes">
      <title>Platform Specific Notes</title>

      <para>The section below has notes for individual platforms.</para>

      <simplesect>
        <title>macOS</title>

        <para>
          Blue uses the right mouse click often to show popup menus. If you do
          not have a right mouse button, you can use ctrl-click for all
          "rt-clicks" that are mentioned in this documentation.
        </para>

        <para>
          To make use of the function key shortcuts (F1-F12), you will need to
          go into System Preferences, choose Keyboard, then enable 
          "Use all F1, F2, etc. keys as standard function keys".           
        </para>

 
      </simplesect>
      
    </section>

  </section>

  <section id="installingCsound">
    <title>Installing Csound</title>

    <para>
      Blue is able to interact with Csound either by calling Csound like a 
      command-line program (classic Blue), or by directly interacting with 
      Csound via the Csound API. Instructions on setting up Blue for each 
      method is described below as well as discussion on benefits and 
      limitations.
    </para>
    
    <section id="commandLineCsound">
      <title>Using Blue with command-line Csound</title>  
        
      <para>
        This may be considered "classical" Blue usage and interaction with 
        Csound as this was the method by which Blue ran with Csound for the 
        first eight years in existance.  The way Blue operates in this mode is 
        by rendering the .Blue project into a temporary CSD file on disk, then
        calling Csound with that temporary CSD file in the same way as if you 
        were on a command-line shell and executing Csound yourself with that
        file.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        The benefit to this mode of Csound usage is that it is easier to switch
        out your version of Csound or use multiple versions of Csound on the 
        same computer.  It is also a little more stable than using the API in 
        that if Csound crashes for some reason, it won't take down Blue with it.
        Also, it may be more performant to use the command-line mode.  These
        benefits however need to be weighed against the benefits of using the 
        API, which is described below.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        To use the command-line version, one needs to set up the Csound 
        executable option for Realtime and Disk Render settings in 
        <link linkend="programOptions">Program Options</link>. 
      </para>
      
    </section>
    
    <section id="csoundAPI">
      <title>Using Blue with the Csound API</title>
    
      <para>
        Enabling Blue to use the Csound API when rendering with Csound opens up
        the ability to manipulate and edit widget values and automations
        in realtime during a render, as well as the ability to use BlueLive on 
        Windows.  Because of its enhancement to the user-experience while 
        rendering and composing, it is the preferred method of using Blue
        with Csound.  Blue should work out-of-the-box with the API if Csound is
        installed using the installers provided on Github, or installed
        via a package manager if on Linux.  
      </para>
      
      <note>
        <title>Note</title>
        <para>Blue currently
        only works with the API if the version of Csound used is compiled
        using 64-bit doubles.  (The float version is not supported 
        when using the API.)  There are technical difficulties in supporting
        two different versions of Csound API in the same build and it is not
        known if or when the float build will be supported.  For users 
        interested in using the float build of Csound with Blue, you will need
        to run Blue using the command-line Csound mode.</para>

        <para>Additionally, the architecture that Csound is compiled for must 
          match the architecture of the Java runtime you are using. For example,
          on Windows, Csound is currently only built for x86_64/amd64 CPU (i.e. 
          64-bit Windows) and not x86  (i.e. 32-bit Windows). In this 
          case, you will need to run Blue using a 64-bit Java Runtime. For OSX,
          this is not an issue as Csound is compiled as a universal binary for
          both i386 and x86_64. On Linux, it is likely that the version of 
          Csound you install/compile and the Java Runtime that you install will
          likely be the same, but if the API does not show as available it may
          be something to check. 
        </para>
           
      </note>
          
      <para>
        Blue uses the CsoundJNI Java binding for Csound. This requires that Blue 
        can find your installed version of Csound but is configured to do so for standard 
        Csound installations. If the API is not enabled
        when starting Blue, the following explains how to setup the API on 
        different platforms.
      </para>
    
      <simplesect>
        <title>Windows</title>
        
        <para>Users using the Windows Installer for Csound should use the 
          double precision version from Github. (This is the default.) After 
          installing, the installer should setup everything such that Blue 
          should work with the API. If for some reason it is unable to do so, you can 
          modify the blue/etc/blue.conf file to tell Blue where to find the 
          csound64.dll. For example, if the directory where csound64.dll is 
          located is in c:\myCsound, open up blue/etc/blue.conf and modify the 
          default so that it contains:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting>
default_options="--branding blue -J-Xms256m -J-Xmx768m -J-Djava.library.path=c:/myCsound"
        </programlisting>
      </simplesect>
      
      <simplesect>
        <title>Linux</title>
        
        <para>
          Linux users should install a doubles version of Csound. The version of 
          Csound found in package repositories should be one compiled for 
          doubles. After installing Csound, modify the blue/bin/blue file. 
          Search for the lines that contain "-J-Djava.library.path=/usr/lib/jni"
          and modify /usr/lib/jni (the default for Debian/Ubuntu-based systems)
          to the directory where libcsound64.so is located.
        </para>
      </simplesect>
      
      <simplesect>
        <title>macOS</title>
        
        <para>macOS users may use the installer for Csound from 
          Github, install Csound with Homebrew, or self-compile. 
          CsoundJNI is configured to find CsoundLib64 in all of the above scenarios for default 
          installations. 
        </para>
            
      </simplesect>
    
      <simplesect>
        <title>Checking whether the API is Enabled</title>
        
        <para>
          To check if the API is enabled, open Blue and open up the Program
          Options. This is available from the Blue->Preferences menu option on
          OSX, and from the Tools->Options menu option Windows and Linux. In
          the Blue tab, under both Disk and Realtime Render settings, there is
          an option called "Render Method".  If Csound 6 is availble on your
          system and Blue was able to find it, it will show a "Csound 6 API"
          option. If the Csound 6 Java API could be loaded, you will only have
          the "Commandline Runner" option which is always available.</para>
      </simplesect>
    
    </section>

  </section>

</section>
