<section id="ceciliaModule">
  <title>CeciliaModule</title>

  <para>Accepts NoteProcessors: no, Supports TimeBehavior: no</para>

  <note>
    <title>Note</title>
    <para>
      This SoundObject is unfinished and not enabled for normal use. This
      information is left here for the future if the module is ever finished and
      reenabled.
    </para>
  </note>

  <simplesect>
    <title>Description</title>

    <para>
      The CeciliaModule is a soundObject that is meant to be compatible with
      modules for the program Cecilia
      (http://www.sourceforge.net/projects/cecilia), created by Alexandre Burton
      and Jean Piche. The CeciliaModule is not as fully featured as Cecilia
      itself as some features found in Cecilia do not make sense within the
      context of Blue.
    </para>

    <para>
      One major advantage of the CeciliaModule is the ability to have as
      manyinstances of a module on the timeline as one likes, all without one
      worrying about variable name clashes or other issues. Blue automatically
      parses and renumbers instruments, ftables, and score statements so that
      they do not interfere with other instances of the same module.
    </para>

  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title>Differences between Cecilia and CeciliaModule</title>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title>
      Modifications required for Cecilia Modules to run in CeciliaModule
    </title>

    <para>
      Cecilia modules require at least one modification before they are able to
      run in Blue, and also must adhere to a few more constraints of design.
    </para>

    <formalpara>
      <title>
        Appending
        <quote>ftable</quote>
        in Instrument Definitions
      </title>

      <para>
        Instruments are required to append the word
        <quote>ftable</quote>
        before any number that is meant to be an ftable. For example:
      </para>

      <programlisting>
        instr 1

        aout oscil 10000, 440, 1

        out aout, aout endin
      </programlisting>

      <para>would have to become:</para>

      <programlisting>
        instr 1

        aout oscil 10000, 440, ftable1

        out aout, aout endin
      </programlisting>

      <para>
        The purpose of this is so that Blue will know what ftable references
        will need to be updated when Blue reassigns ftable numbers.
      </para>

    </formalpara>

  </simplesect>

</section>
