<section id="instanceObject">
  <title>Instance</title>
         
  <para>Accepts NoteProcessors: yes</para>
         
  <para>A SoundObject that points to a SoundObject in the SoundObject library. 
    The content of the SoundObject is not editable except by editing the 
    SoundObject in the library to which the instance is pointing to. If editing 
    the SoundObject in the library, all instances that point to that 
    SoundObject will be changed.
  </para>
  <para>When clicking on an Instance object to edit it, the SoundObject from 
    the library will show its editor instead in the SoundObject edit area, but 
    it will be clearly marked that the user is currently editing a library 
    SoundObject and not an individual SoundObject.
  </para>
  <para>
    The instance object is very useful if your work entails using many
    variations of single source of material. For example, you can take a 
    SoundObject that represents a drum pattern, then make many Instances of 
    that pattern and add them to your project. If you want to later change the
    base pattern, it will update everywhere that there are Instance objects 
    pointing to it.
  </para>
  <para>
    Another example, if you have a SoundObject that represents a motive or 
    melodic fragment, you can put it into the SoundObject library, then make 
    10 instances of it, adding noteProcessors to do things like transpose or 
    get the retrograde, etc. Later, if you decide you want to change the base 
    material, you'd only have to edit it once within the library. All Instance 
    objects pointing to the changed object will be updated and will maintain 
    all of their transformations and relationships that were added via 
    NoteProcessors.
  </para>
  
  <para>
    If you later decide that you want to work with the original material where 
    you have an Instance and want to break the link, replacing the instance 
    with a copy of the original to modify, you can convert the Instance object 
    to a GenericScore. To do this, you can use one of two methods:
  </para>
  
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      Right-click the Instance object and choose "Convert to Generic Score"
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      Go the SoundObject Library, select the original and use "Copy", then 
      select the Instance object and use "Replace with SoundObject in Buffer"
    </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>


  
</section>