
<section id="jmask">
    <title>JMask</title>
    <para>Accepts NoteProcessors: yes</para>
    <para>JMask is GUI score generating soundObject based on Andre Bartetzki's
        <ulink url="http://www.bartetzki.de/en/software.html">CMask
        </ulink>.
JMask currently supports all features of CMask except field precision, 
though support for this feature is planned. Users of JMask are encouraged to
read the CMask manual available at Andre Bartetzki's site to get familiar with
CMask concepts as they are represented 1:1 in JMask.
    </para>
    <para>JMask builds on top of CMask's concepts and feature set by providing
the user a graphical way to edit parameter values, tables, masks, etc.  Also, by 
using JMask, the user's projects are guaranteed to run on all Blue 
installations, while using CMask from Blue requires anyone opening and using
the project to have CMask installed on their system.
    </para>
    <para>The following documentation for JMask will assume the user is familiar
with CMask and that the user has read through the CMask manual available 
from the link above. The following will discuss how to use JMask, covering how
the CMask features are implemented in JMask and how to work with the user 
interface.  Over time, this manual entry for JMask will attempt to grow to be
self sufficient and not require knowledge of CMask, but for now familiarity
with CMask is suggested.</para>

<section id="jmaskOverview">
    <title>Overview</title>
    
    <para>A single JMask object is equivalent to one CMask field. A single
    JMask object holds a collection of Parameters, one for each pfield to be
    generated in the score. Each of the Parameter types in CMask is
    available in JMask: </para>
    
    <table>
        <title>Parameter Types</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
            <thead>
                <row>
                    <entry>Type</entry>
                    <entry>Description</entry>
                </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
                <row>
                    <entry>Constant</entry>
                    <entry>Generate the given value when generating values 
                    for notes</entry>
                </row>
                
                <row>
                    <entry>Item List</entry>
                    <entry>Generates values from a list of values given by the 
                    user. Options for generation include cycling through the 
                    list (cycle), going backwards and forwards through the list 
                    (swing), going through the list in random order using all 
                    values once before repeating (heap), and choosing a random 
                    list item (random).</entry>
                </row>
                
                <row>
                    <entry>Segment</entry>
                    <entry>Generates values along a user-defined line.</entry>
                </row>
                
                <row>
                    <entry>Random</entry>
                    <entry>Generates a random value.</entry>
                </row>
                
                <row>
                    <entry>Probability</entry>
                    <entry>Generates a randomized value that is weighted by the
                    given probability type and the configuration of the 
                    parameters of that probability type.</entry>
                </row>
                
                <row>
                    <entry>Oscillator</entry>
                    <entry>Generates values that oscillate in a given period 
                    using different user-chosen shapes.</entry>
                </row>
                
            </tbody>
        </tgroup>
    </table>
    
    <para>Beyond the Parameters, JMask supports the three modifier types found
    in CMask: Masks, Quantizers, and Accumulators.  Certain parameters support
    different modifiers, and their support by paramater type is listed below:
    </para>
    
    <table>
        <title>Parameter Modifier Support</title>
        <tgroup cols="4">
            <thead>
                <row>
                    <entry>Type</entry>
                    <entry>Supports Mask</entry>
                    <entry>Supports Quantizer</entry>
                    <entry>Supports Accumulator</entry>
                </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
                <row>
                    <entry>Constant</entry>
                    <entry>No</entry>
                    <entry>No</entry>
                    <entry>Yes</entry>
                </row>
                
                <row>
                    <entry>List</entry>
                    <entry>No</entry>
                    <entry>No</entry>
                    <entry>Yes</entry>
                </row>
                
                <row>
                    <entry>Segment</entry>
                    <entry>No</entry>
                    <entry>Yes</entry>
                    <entry>Yes</entry>
                </row>
                
                <row>
                    <entry>Random</entry>
                    <entry>No</entry>
                    <entry>Yes</entry>
                    <entry>Yes</entry>
                </row>
                
                <row>
                    <entry>Probability</entry>
                    <entry>Yes</entry>
                    <entry>Yes</entry>
                    <entry>Yes</entry>
                </row>
                
                <row>
                    <entry>Oscillator</entry>
                    <entry>Yes</entry>
                    <entry>Yes</entry>
                    <entry>Yes</entry>
                </row>
                
            </tbody>
        </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>JMask also supports the use of a seed value.  When enabling the use of seeding, the seed value will be used to initialize the pseudo-random number generator used in randomized operations.  This allows the user to set a seed and get consistently reproducible results. The default is to use the system time to seed the random number generator, thus giving different results each render.</para>
</section>

<section id="jmaskInterface">
    <title>Using the JMask Interface</title>
    
    <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/jmask.png"
                        format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    
    <para>
        The JMask SoundObject Editor allows for viewing the editors for all of
        the assigned parameters.  Parameters are each set to generate values for
        one pfield.  On the top side of each row is the Parameter Edit 
        Panel.  This panel shows a number at the top that corresponds to what
        pfield this parameter will generate values for, as well as the field 
        name. To change things about the Parameter, right-click the panel to 
        show a popup menu as shown in the image above.  The options are described below:
    </para>
    
    <variablelist>
      <title>Parameter Edit Options</title>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Add Parameter Before</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Create a new Parameter and insert it before the Parameter clicked
          on by mouse. When this option is selected, a dialog will appear with
          a dropdown of options of what type of Parameter to add.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Add Parameter After</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Create a new Parameter and insert it after the Parameter clicked
          on by mouse. When this option is selected, a dialog will appear with
          a dropdown of options of what type of Parameter to add.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Remove Parameter</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Remove this Parameter.  Will not be allowed if trying to edit 
          parameters 1-3 as JMask requires a minimum of 3 pfields.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Change Parameter Type</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Choose a different type of Parameter and replace the current one
          with the selected one.  Any edits from the old Parameter will be lost
          once a new parameter type is chosen.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Push Up</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Move the selected Parameter to before the previous Parameter.
          Example: Push up parameter at pfield 5 to pfield 4, moving what was
          previously at 4 to 5.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Push Down</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Move the selected Parameter to after the next Parameter.
          Example: Push down parameter at pfield 4 to pfield 5, moving what was
          previously at 5 to 4.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Mask</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enable/disable using a Mask with this parameter.  If enabled, 
          the Mask editor will appear, and if disabled, the Mask editor will
          disappear.  This menu option will not show for those Parameters that
          do not support Masks.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Quantizer</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enable/disable using a Quantizer with this parameter.  If enabled, 
          the Quantizer editor will appear, and if disabled, the Quantizer 
          editor will disappear.  This menu option will not show for those 
          Parameters that do not support Quantizers.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Accumulator</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enable/disable using an Accumulator with this parameter.  
          If enabled, the Accumulator editor will appear, and if disabled, the 
          Accumulator editor will disappear.  This menu option will not show 
          for those Parameters which do not support Accumulators.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>
    
    <para>Beyond the basics of moving around Parameters, adding new ones, and
    choosing whether to enable Masks, Quantizeres, and Accumulators, one can
    also choose to show/hide Parameters by using the popup menu that appears
    when choosing the down arrow button in the JMask title bar, as shown in the
    screenshot below.        
    </para>
    
    <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/jmask2.png"
                        format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para>To edit the field name, double click the Parameter Edit Panel. A 
      dialog will appear where you can modify the field name, as shown below:
    </para>

    <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/jmask_field_name.png"
                        format="PNG" />
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
    
    <para>Beyond these basics for working with the Parameters in general, each
    Parameter type has its own editor, each customized for the values and 
    options allowable for each Parameter.  Currently, documentation is omitted
    for each Parameter's GUI as they correspond in feature and parameters as
    CMask, and the user is encouraged to consult the CMask manual for more 
    information on editing each Parameter.</para>
    
    
    
</section>

</section>
