<section id="installation">
  <title>Installation</title>

  <section id="requirements">
    <title>Requirements</title>

    <para>
      blue requires a Java 6 (also known as 1.6) or greater JVM (Java Virtual 
      Machine). To test to see if you have a JVM installed and what version, at 
      a command prompt type "java -version". If you see something along the 
      lines of "command not found" then you need to install a Java Virtual 
      Machine.
    </para>

    <para>A Java JVM for Linux, Windows, Mac OSX, and Solaris can be found at:
    </para>

    <para>
        <ulink url="http://www.java.com">http://www.java.com</ulink>
    </para>

    <para>
      From this page, the correct download for the JRE (Java Runtime 
      Environment) for your platform should be chosen automatically for you. 
      (Note: There are two main releases of Java, the JRE, and the JDK 
      (Java Development Kit). You only need the JRE to run blue, though if you
      are interested in developing in Java you need the JDK.)
    </para>

  </section>

  <section id="installingBlue">
    <title>Installing blue</title>

    <para>
      To install blue, you should download the latest ZIP file from
      the blue Sourceforge page
      <ulink url="http://www.sourceforge.net/projects/bluemusic">here</ulink>. 
      Unzip the file to a location of your choice. After unzipping, locate the 
      bin folder and use either the "blue" script or "blue.exe", depending if 
      you are on Linux/OSX or Windows. For OSX users, unzipping the zip should 
      produce a blue.app directory that will appear as a clickable application. 
      Simply double-clicking this should start blue.</para>
    <para>
      Note: After starting blue, 
      you may want to explore the example projects and pieces found in the 
      blue/example folder (or right-click and explore contents of 
      blue.app/example if on OSX).
    </para>

    <section id="platformNotes">
      <title>Platform Specific Notes</title>

      <para>The section below has notes for individual platforms.</para>

      <simplesect>
        <title>Mac OSX</title>

        <para>
          Blue uses the right mouse click often to show popup menus. If you do
          not have a right mouse button, you can use ctrl-click for all
          "rt-clicks" that are mentioned in this documentation.
        </para>

        <para>
          To make use of the function key shortcuts (F1-F12), you will need to
          go into System Preferences, choose Keyboard, then enable 
          "Use all F1, F2, etc. keys as standard function keys".           
        </para>

 
      </simplesect>
      
      <simplesect>
        <title>Linux</title>

        <para>
          For 64-bit systems, you may run into issues when running blue with the
          API enabled where modifying widget values is not reflected in 
          performance. This is likely due to the Csound Java API being compiled
          with SWIG &lt; 2.0.  As of the time of this writing, the version of 
          Csound in Debian Stable for amd64 is compiled with SWIG 1.3.0, and 
          does not work with blue.  To work around this, you can install a 
          newer version of Csound if available (i.e. from a testing repo), or 
          compile Csound yourself and ensure you are using SWIG version 2.0 or greater. 
        </para>

      </simplesect>

    </section>

  </section>

  <section id="installingCsound">
    <title>Installing Csound</title>

    <para>
      blue is able to interact with Csound either by calling Csound like a 
      command-line program (classic blue), or by directly interacting with 
      Csound via the Csound API. Instructions on setting up blue for each 
      method is described below as well as discussion on benefits and 
      limitations.
    </para>
    
    <section id="commandLineCsound">
      <title>Using blue with command-line Csound</title>  
        
      <para>
        This may be considered "classical" blue usage and interaction with 
        Csound as this was the method by which blue ran with Csound for the 
        first eight years in existance.  The way blue operates in this mode is 
        by rendering the .blue project into a temporary CSD file on disk, then
        calling Csound with that temporary CSD file in the same way as if you 
        were on a command-line shell and executing Csound yourself with that
        file.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        The benefit to this mode of Csound usage is that it is easier to switch
        out your version of Csound or use multiple versions of Csound on the 
        same computer.  It is also a little more stable than using the API in 
        that if Csound crashes for some reason, it won't take down blue with it.
        Also, it may be more performant to use the command-line mode.  These
        benefits however need to be weighed against the benefits of using the 
        API, which is described below.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        To use the command-line version, one needs to set up the Csound 
        executable option for Realtime and Disk Render settings in 
        <link linkend="programOptions">Program Options</link>. 
      </para>
      
    </section>
    
    <section id="csoundAPI">
      <title>Using blue with the Csound API</title>
    
      <para>
        Enabling blue to use the Csound API when rendering with Csound opens up
        the ability to manipulate and edit widget values and automations
        in realtime during a render, as well as the ability to use blueLive on 
        Windows.  Because of its enhancement to the user-experience while 
        rendering and composing, it is now the preferred method of using blue
        with Csound.  blue should work out-of-the-box with the API if Csound is
        installed using the installers provided on SourceForge, or installed
        via a package manager if on Linux.  
      </para>
      
      <note>
        <title>Note</title>
        <para>blue currently
        only works with the API if the version of Csound used is compiled
        using 64-bit doubles.  (The float version is not currently supported 
        when using the API.)  There are technical difficulties in supporting
        two different versions of Csound API in the same build and it is not
        known if or when the float build will be supported.  For users 
        interested in using the float build of Csound with blue, you will need
        to run blue using the command-line Csound mode.</para>
      </note>
          
      <para>
        The Java API for Csound is split into two parts: the csnd.jar file as 
        well as the lib_jcsound.so native library (this file is csound 
        jcsound.dll on Windows, and lib_jcsound.jnilib on Mac OSX). blue comes 
        with it's own copy of csnd.jar, so to use the API from blue it will need 
        to have access to the native library to work. If the API is not enabled
        for use out-of-the-box, the following explains how to setup the API on 
        different platforms.
      </para>
    
      <simplesect>
        <title>Windows</title>
        
        <para>Users using the Windows Installer for Csound should use the 
          doubles version from SourceForge (has -d in the name). After 
          installing, the installer should setup everything such that blue 
          should work with the API. If for some reason it is unable to do so, or 
          you have compiled Csound yourself and the location of jcsound.dll is 
          different from where it is installed with the installer, you can 
          modify the blue/etc/blue.conf file to tell blue where to find the 
          jcsound.dll. For example, if the directory where jcsound.dll is 
          located is in c:\myCsound, open up blue/etc/blue.conf and modify the 
          default so that it contains:
        </para>
        
        <programlisting>
default_options="--branding blue -J-Xms256m -J-Xmx768m -J-Djava.library.path=c:/myCsound"
        </programlisting>
      </simplesect>
      
      <simplesect>
        <title>Linux</title>
        
        <para>
          Linux users should install a doubles version of Csound. The version of 
          Csound found in package repositories should be one compiled for 
          doubles. After installing Csound and the Java interface for Csound,
          locate where lib_jcsound.so is and modify the blue/bin/blue file. 
          Search for the lines that contain "-J-Djava.library.path=/usr/lib/jni"
          and modify /usr/lib/jni (the default for Debian/Ubuntu-based systems)
          to the directory where lib_jcsound.so is located.
        </para>
      </simplesect>
      
      <simplesect>
        <title>Mac OSX</title>
        
        <para>Mac OSX users should use the installer for Csound from 
          Sourceforge. The installer should install both the float and doubles 
          version of Csound. The lib_jcsound.jnilib will be installed into
          /Library/Java/Extensions.  If you are compiling your own version of 
          Csound, you can remove the symlink in /Library/Java/Extensions and 
          either symlink your your version there or copy it into that folder.
        </para>
            
      </simplesect>
    
      <simplesect>
        <title>Checking the API is Enabled</title>
        
        <para>
          To check if the API is enabled, open blue and open up the Project 
          menu. On this menu is an option called "Use Csound API".  If the 
          menu is not enabled (it will be greyed out, and you will be unable
          to select the menu item), then the blue could not load up the Csound
          API.  Note, this is different than if it is enabled but not selected.
          Whether the menu is enabled or not tells if the API is found and can
          be used, while selecting it and making it checked or not tells blue
          if you want to use the API or the commandline runner.  If the API is
          not found or the is not selected, then blue will use the commandline
          runner.
        </para>
          
      </simplesect>
    
    </section>

  </section>

</section>
