<section id="programOptions">
  <title>Setting Up Program Options</title>

  <para>
    The first thing you'll want to do is set up your Program Options. Some
    settings are required for features of blue to work (i.e. Render Settings,
    the Csound Documentation Root for opening opcode help), others are there to
    help setup your project defaults and save you time when creating new
    projects.
  </para>

  <para>
    To open up the Program Options dialog, go to the File menu and click on
    "Program Options".
  </para>

  <simplesect>
    <title>General</title>

    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Program Options - General</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/programOptions_general.png" format="PNG" 
          scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <variablelist>
      <title>General Options</title>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Csound Documentation Root</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This is the url of the root of your Csound Documentation. blue uses
            this for opening up Csound Documentation as well as when opening up
            help for an opcode. The Csound Documentation Root can be local (i.e.
            "file:///home/user/blue/manual/" or 
            "file://c:/Programs and Files/blue/manual/")
            or online (i.e. "http://www.csounds.com/manual/html/").
          </para>

          <para>
            You can get the Csound html documentation from
            <ulink url="http://www.csounds.com/manual" />
            .
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Work Directory</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The default directory that blue should open when loading/saving blue
            project files.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Maintain Last Window State</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Enables saving of window location and size. If enabled, upon
            starting of program, window states will be restored.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>New User Defaults Enabled</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Enables default text for different objects in blue. Curently this
            affects:
          </para>

          <itemizedlist>

            <listitem>
              <para>CodeRepository - when adding new Code Snippet</para>
            </listitem>

          </itemizedlist>

        </listitem>

      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Draw Flat SoundObject Borders</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Enables older flat drawing style of SoundObject borders on the score
            timeline.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Draw Alpha Background on Marquee</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If this is enabled, when selecting a group of SoundObjects on the
            Score Timeline the marquee that is drawn to show the selection area
            will paint with an alpha-transparent white background. (May slow
            down performance when enabled.)
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Show Csound Output</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If this is enabled, output from rendering with Csound will be shown
            in the Csound Output Dialog (accessible from the Window menu or
            available with the F7 shortcut).  If disabled, output will be shown
            in the std.out of the console that opens when blue starts.  (If
            the blue starter script has been modified not to show the console
            by using javaw instead of java, then the output will not be able
            to be seen).  It is recommended to enable this option.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Message Colors Enabled</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
             Since Csound5, the default for printed messages is to show them
             with colors by using ANSI text modifiers.  However, this only works
             within ANSI-compliant consoles, and does not work within blue's
             Csound Output Dialog.  It is recommended to keep this disabled if
             the "Show Csound Output" option is enabled.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Language</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Which language to use for blue. This affects the labels of the User
            Interface, messages given to the user in dialog boxes, menu titles,
            etc. (Translation files may not always be up to of date so some UI
            items may not be translated when not in English.)
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>


  </simplesect>


  <simplesect>
    <title>Project Defaults</title>

    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Program Options - Project Defaults</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/programOptions_projectDefaults.png"
            format="PNG" scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para>
      These settings are used whenever new projects are created as defaults for
      the project, unless a default.blue file is found in the user's blue home
      directory, in which case the settings from the default.blue file are used.
    </para>


    <variablelist>
      <title>Project Defaults</title>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Author</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Default author to use in new projects.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Mixer Enabled</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enable using the blue Mixer in new projects by default.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title>Playback</title>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Program Options - Playback</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/programOptions_playBack.png" format="PNG" 
                     scalefit="1" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <variablelist>
      <title>Playback</title>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Time Pointer Animation Rate</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Rate of animation for time pointer to update when playing back in
            realtime, expressed in frames per second. For example, the default
            value of 20 means the time pointer is updated 20 times per second,
            giving a smooth animation rate. Slower values may be desirable on
            slower computers if the playback pointer is affecting performance.
          </para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Latency Correction</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Float value in seconds to use as a correction for audio latency in
            the user's sound playback mechanism. For example, if latency is
            quite bad on your soundcard and there is a delay of .5 seconds
            between when audio is passed to your soundcard and when the audio is
            actually realized from the DAC, the visual time pointer for blue may
            appear ahead in time of what is being heard. Using a .5 value for
            latency correction would correct for this.
          </para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title>Utility</title>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Program Options - Utility</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/programOptions_utility.png" format="PNG"
          scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject>
          <phrase>Program Options - Utility</phrase>
        </textobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Program Options - Utility</para>
        </caption>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <variablelist>
      <title>Utility</title>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Csound Executable</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This is the command for what version of Csound to execute when
            blue uses utilities that depend on Csound (for example, freezing
            SoundObjects, the SoundFont Viewer utility). The default value of
            "csound" works if you have a version of Csound in your path named
            "csound". You may use any command here that would call Csound
            that would work as if you were running csound from a terminal.

            <note>
              <title>Note</title>
              <para>
                The value defined for Csound Executable should only be the
                command to call Csound and no other flags should be added
                here.
              </para>
            </note>

          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Freeze Flags</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            These are the flags for Csound that blue uses when performing
            SoundObject freezing. Defaults are "-Ado" for Mac and "-Wdo" for all
            other operating systems. Users may wish to modify this value if they
            would their frozen soundObjects to be in a different format, i.e.
            32-bit float soundfiles.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title>Realtime Render</title>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Program Options - Realtime</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/programOptions_realtime.png" format="PNG"
          scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <variablelist>
      <title>Project Settings</title>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Csound Executable</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This is a command for what version of Csound to execute when
            blue renders the project in realtime. The default value of
            "csound" works if you have a version of Csound in your path named
            "csound". You may use any command here that would call csound
            that would work as if you were running csound from a terminal.</para>

            <para>Using the button marked "..." on the right will open up a file
            dialog so that you can find and select the Csound executable to use
            to run Csound.</para>
            
            <para>If you are using the API, you still need to have something 
              set here. You can set it to "csound" in that case.
            </para>

            <note>
              <title>Note</title>
              <para>
                The value defined for Csound Executable should only be the
                command to call Csound and no other flags should be added
                here.
              </para>
            </note>

        </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Render Method</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
                Choose which render service to use for rendering the project. 
                When the program loads, Blue will first try to see if the Csound
                6 API is available and if so, show that option here.  If it can
                not find the Csound 6 API, it will search for the Csound 5 API
                and show that option here instead if it is found.  If neither is
                found, the Commandline Runner option will always be available to
                use.                
            </para>

            <para>Note: If you have both Csound 5 and Csound 6 installed, you 
                can force Blue to ignore Csound 6 on load by adding 
                "-J-DDISABLE_CSOUND=true" to the blue/etc/blue.conf file in the
                default_options section. On OSX, this will be in 
                blue.app/Contents/Resources/blue/etc/blue.conf.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>sr</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Default sr to use for realtime settings in new projects.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>ksmps</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Default ksmps to use for realtime settings in new projects.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>0dbfs</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Default value to use for 0dbfs.  Also, the checkbox denotes 
              whether projects should use 0dbfs by default or not.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <title>Devices</title>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Audio Driver</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Driver to use for audio input and output. This is equivalent
          to using the --rtaudio= flag setting on the commandline.
          </para>

          <para>Enabling the checkbox determines if this value will be used at
          all when rendering, and if so, will use the value from the dropdown
          as the driver setting.
          </para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Audio Out</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Audio output device to use.  Equivalent to using -o flag setting
            on the commandline.  This setting is dependent on the setting used
            on the audio driver setting.  Using a value of "dac" will use the
            default device for the driver.
          </para>

          <para>
            The value of this setting will be used for all projects that set
            "Audio Out" enabled in the project-level realtime render settings.
          </para>

          <para>
            By selecting the [...] button to the right of this field, blue will
            try to detect what devices are available for the chosen Audio
            Driver. If blue is able to find the devices, a popup dialog will
            appear with a list of available devices.  Selecting from the popup
            will then populate the textfield with the correct device string that
            Csound will use to choose the device requested.

            <note>
              <title>Note</title>
              <para>
                If the driver is chosen but not enabled for use via its
                checkbox, when auto-detecting, blue will check for devices
                against the default driver and not necessarily what is in the
                dropdown. Please be sure that if you are planning to use the
                auto-detect feature with a particular driver that you also
                select the driver and enable it with the checkbox.
              </para>
            </note>
          </para>

          <para>Enabling the checkbox determines if this device will be enabled
          by default for new projects.
          </para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Audio In</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Audio input device to use.  Equivalent to using -i flag setting
            on the commandline.  This setting is dependent on the setting used
            on the audio driver setting.  Using a value of "adc" will use the
            default device for the driver.
          </para>

          <para>
            The value of this setting will be used for all projects that set
            "Audio In" enabled in the project-level realtime render settings.
          </para>

          <para>
            By selecting the [...] button to the right of this field, blue will
            try to detect what devices are available for the chosen Audio
            Driver. If blue is able to find the devices, a popup dialog will
            appear with a list of available devices.  Selecting from the popup
            will then populate the textfield with the correct device string that
            Csound will use to choose the device requested.

            <note>
              <title>Note</title>
              <para>
                If the driver is chosen but not enabled for use via its
                checkbox, when auto-detecting, blue will check for devices
                against the default driver and not necessarily what is in the
                dropdown. Please be sure that if you are planning to use the
                auto-detect feature with a particular driver that you also
                select the driver and enable it with the checkbox.
              </para>
            </note>
          </para>


          <para>Enabling the checkbox determines if this device will be enabled
          by default for new projects.
          </para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>MIDI Driver</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Driver to use for MIDI input and output. This is equivalent
          to using the --rtmidi= flag setting on the commandline.
          </para>

          <para>Enabling the checkbox determines if this value will be used at
          all when rendering, and if so, will use the value from the dropdown
          as the driver setting.
          </para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>MIDI Out</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            MIDI output device to use.  Equivalent to using -Q flag setting
            on the commandline.  This setting is dependent on the setting used
            on the MIDI driver setting.
          </para>

          <para>
            The value of this setting will be used for all projects that set
            "MIDI Out" enabled in the project-level realtime render settings.
          </para>

          <para>
            By selecting the [...] button to the right of this field, blue will
            try to detect what devices are available for the chosen MIDI
            Driver. If blue is able to find the devices, a popup dialog will
            appear with a list of available devices.  Selecting from the popup
            will then populate the textfield with the correct device string that
            Csound will use to choose the device requested.

            <note>
              <title>Note</title>
              <para>
                If the driver is chosen but not enabled for use via its
                checkbox, when auto-detecting, blue will check for devices
                against the default driver and not necessarily what is in the
                dropdown. Please be sure that if you are planning to use the
                auto-detect feature with a particular driver that you also
                select the driver and enable it with the checkbox.
              </para>
            </note>
          </para>


          <para>Enabling the checkbox determines if this device will be enabled
          by default for new projects.
          </para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>MIDI In</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            MIDI input device to use.  Equivalent to using -M flag setting
            on the commandline.  This setting is dependent on the setting used
            on the audio driver setting.
          </para>

          <para>
            The value of this setting will be used for all projects that set
            "MIDI In" enabled in the project-level realtime render settings.
          </para>

          <para>
            By selecting the [...] button to the right of this field, blue will
            try to detect what devices are available for the chosen MIDI
            Driver. If blue is able to find the devices, a popup dialog will
            appear with a list of available devices.  Selecting from the popup
            will then populate the textfield with the correct device string that
            Csound will use to choose the device requested.

            <note>
              <title>Note</title>
              <para>
                If the driver is chosen but not enabled for use via its
                checkbox, when auto-detecting, blue will check for devices
                against the default driver and not necessarily what is in the
                dropdown. Please be sure that if you are planning to use the
                auto-detect feature with a particular driver that you also
                select the driver and enable it with the checkbox.
              </para>
            </note>
          </para>


          <para>Enabling the checkbox determines if this device will be enabled
          by default for new projects.
          </para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <title>Buffer Settings</title>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Software Buffer</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Size of software sample buffer to use (-b).  For more information,
          see CommandFlags section of Csound manual for settings.
          </para>

          <para>Enabling the checkbox determines if this value will be used at
          all when rendering.
          </para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Hardware Buffer</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Size of hardware sample buffer to use (-B).  For more information,
          see CommandFlags section of Csound manual for settings.
          </para>

          <para>Enabling the checkbox determines if this value will be used at
          all when rendering.
          </para>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <title>Message Level</title>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Note Amplitudes</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
          Enables note amplitude messages from Csound (-m1)
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Out-of-Range Messages</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Enables samples out of range messages from Csound (-m2)
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Warnings</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Enables warning messages from Csound (-m4)
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Benchmark Information</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
          Enables benchmark information from Csound (-m128)
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <title>Advanced Settings</title>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Advanced Settings</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
          Extra flags to append to the commandline that might not be covered by
          options in the UI.  Pressing the [?] button will open the
          documentation for the Csound command flags (Csound Documentation Root
          but be set for this to work).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title>Disk Render</title>
    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Program Options - Disk Render</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/programOptions_diskRender.png"
            format="PNG" scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <variablelist>
      <title>Project Settings</title>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Csound Executable</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This is a command for what version of csound to execute when
            blue renders the project to disk. The default value of
            "csound" works if you have a version of Csound in your path named
            "csound". You may use any command here that would call csound
            that would work as if you were running csound from a terminal.</para>

            <para>Using the button marked "..." on the right will open up a file
            dialog so that you can find and select the csound executable to use
            to run Csound.</para>

            <note>
              <title>Note</title>
              <para>
                The value defined for Csound Executable should only be the
                command to call Csound and no other flags should be added
                here.
              </para>
            </note>

        </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Render Method</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
                Choose which render service to use for rendering the project. 
                When the program loads, Blue will first try to see if the Csound
                6 API is available and if so, show that option here.  If it can
                not find the Csound 6 API, it will search for the Csound 5 API
                and show that option here instead if it is found.  If neither is
                found, the Commandline Runner option will always be available to
                use.                
            </para>

            <para>Note: If you have both Csound 5 and Csound 6 installed, you 
                can force Blue to ignore Csound 6 on load by adding 
                "-J-DDISABLE_CSOUND=true" to the blue/etc/blue.conf file in the
                default_options section. On OSX, this will be in 
                blue.app/Contents/Resources/blue/etc/blue.conf.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>sr</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Default sr to use for disk render settings in new projects.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>ksmps</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Default ksmps to use for disk render settings in new projects.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>nchnls</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Default nchnls to use for disk render settings in new projects.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        
        <varlistentry>
          <term>0dbfs</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Default value to use for 0dbfs.  Also, the checkbox denotes 
              whether projects should use 0dbfs by default or not.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <title>Render and Play Command</title>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Enabled</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Enable using custom play command when using "Render and Play". 
          If not enabled, blue's built-in audio player will be used once the
          project is finished rendering to disk.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Command</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Command to call after finished rendering a project. The command
          line given should use the $outfile property where the name of the 
          generated audio file should be passed to the program.  For example,
          to open the rendered audio with VLC on Mac OSX, you can use this 
          command line:</para>
          
          <programlisting>open -a VLC $outfile</programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <title>File Output Settings</title>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>File Format</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>File format to use (i.e. WAV, AIFF, AU, etc.)</para>

          <para>
            Enabling the checkbox determines if this value will be used at all
            when rendering.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Sample Format</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Sample format to use. The default of SHORT is the same as 16-bit
            integer audio (the same as used for CD's). Other formats are
            available in the dropdown to use.
          </para>

          <para>
            Enabling the checkbox determines if this value will be used at all
            when rendering.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Save Peak Information in Header</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Save the peak information in the file header.</para>

           <para>
            Enabling the checkbox determines if this value will be used at all
            when rendering.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Dither Output</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use dither on output.</para>

           <para>
            Enabling the checkbox determines if this value will be used at all
            when rendering.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Rewrite Header while Rendering</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Rewrite the file header while rendering.  This makes it possible
            to play the audio file in the middle of a render and is useful
            when the rendering of the project will take a very long time.
            However, it does slow down overall render time.
          </para>

           <para>
            Enabling the checkbox determines if this value will be used at all
            when rendering.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <title>Message Level</title>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Note Amplitudes</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
          Enables note amplitude messages from Csound (-m1)
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Out-of-Range Messages</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Enables samples out of range messages from Csound (-m2)
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Warnings</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Enables warning messages from Csound (-m4)
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Benchmark Information</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
          Enables benchmark information from Csound (-m128)
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

    <variablelist>
      <title>Advanced Settings</title>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Advanced Settings</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
          Extra flags to append to the commandline that might not be covered by
          options in the UI.  Pressing the [?] button will open the
          documentation for the Csound command flags (Csound Documentation Root
          but be set for this to work).
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title>MIDI</title>
    <!--<screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Program Options - Disk Render</screeninfo>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/programOptions_diskRender.png"
            format="PNG" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>-->
    
    <para>These settings are for blue's MIDI input, used with 
      <link linkend="blueLive">blueLive</link>. The table shows what devices
      are currently available, and whether they are enabled for use with 
      blueLive or not.  You can use the "rescan" button to search for devices
      if you have just plugged in a device.
    </para>
    
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title>OSC</title>
    
    <para>
      This allows you to set what port blue will listen to for incoming OSC 
      messages. Defaults to 8000. The following messages are understood by blue:
    </para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
          
      <listitem>
        <para>/score/play</para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para>/score/stop</para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para>/score/rewind</para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para>/score/markerNext</para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para>/score/markerPrevious</para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para>/blueLive/onOff</para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para>/blueLive/recompile</para>
      </listitem>
        
      <listitem>
        <para>/blueLive/allNotesOff</para>
      </listitem>
        
      <listitem>
        <para>/blueLive/toggleMidiInput</para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>
    
  </simplesect>

</section>
