<section id="mixer">
  <title>Mixer</title>

  <screenshot>
    <screeninfo>Mixer</screeninfo>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/mixer.png" format="PNG" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>

  <para>
    The Mixer system in Blue allows for graphically editing levels for
    instruments, applying pre- and post-fader effects, and routing and mixing of
    signals through subchannels.
  </para>


  <section>
    <title>Architecture</title>

    <para>
      The Mixer system has three panel sections:

      <variablelist>
        <title>Mixer Sections</title>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Channels</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Channels are auto-created and bound to Instrument ID's in the
              Orchestra for a Project. In the Mixer Dialog they are located in
              the first section on the left within a splitpane that separates
              them from the SubChannels. Channels can be set to route to either
              SubChannels or directly to the Master Channel.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>SubChannels</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              SubChannels are user-created and are located in the center section
              of the Mixer Dialog, on the right side of the splitpane. Channels
              can be set to route to SubChannels, and SubChannels can route into
              other SubChannels or out to the Master Channel.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Master Channel</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              The Master Channel is located on the right side of the Mixer
              Dialog. There is only one master Channel per project which all
              channel and subchannel signals ultimately route through.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

      </variablelist>
    </para>

    <para>
      Each channel allows for applying effects to the incoming signal either
      pre- or post-fader.
    </para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Using the Mixer</title>

    <para>
      For most MIDI-based music composition environments, the typical user
      interaction with a Mixer system is that users first create tracks on a
      timeline, and for each track an audio channel is automatically bound in
      the mixer. The user then selects an instrument for that track(if it is a
      MIDI track); MIDI information from the track is routed to the instrument
      and that instrument generates audio signals. If the instrument happens to
      be a software synthesizer, the audio signals are then usually taken from
      the instrument and routed out to the Mixer channel that has been bound to
      that track.
    </para>

    <para>
      However, since Blue does not bind music information on a SoundLayer to an
      instrument (you can have heterogenous note data generated in any
      soundObject for any number of instruments, a flexibility which allows for
      soundObjects to be more representative of musical ideas), and nor does it
      bind SoundLayers to channels, the abstraction of the musical system and
      the interaction with the Mixer system requires different handling.
    </para>

    <para>
      In Blue's Mixer system, Mixer channels are automatically bound to
      instruments by their instrument ID. Binding to ID and not per-instrument
      in the Orchestra allows for the case where users have set multiple
      instruments to the same instrument ID but only having one which is
      enabled. If you then disable one and then enable another instrument to
      test out different instruments with the same musical note data, the mixer
      channel's settings will be maintained for the new instrument as it is
      bound by ID.
    </para>

    <para>
      Channels in themselves can not be created or removed directly by the user,
      but are automatically added or removed depending on how how instruments
      are added and removed from the project's orchestra. For cases of when an
      instrument has an ID and a user wishes to change the ID, if the new ID
      already exists and a channel is already created, the old channel is
      removed as long as no other instrument has the old ID. If the new channel
      ID has no existing mixer channel bound to it and if the channel for the
      old ID only has one instrument with that ID (the instrument that is
      changing ID's), the bound mixer channel is simply reassigned to the new ID
      and maintains its settings.
    </para>

    <para>
      Subchannels are added by right-clicking with in the SubChannels area and
      choosing "Add SubChannel" from the popup menu. To remove a subchannel
      right-click the channel strip to be removed and select "Remove" from the
      popup menu.
    </para>

    <para>
      At the bottom of every Channel and SubChannel strip is an output dropdown
      box to choose where to route that Chanel's audio to. For SubChannels, they
      can only route to other SubChannels which lead to the Master Channel,
      meaning that there is no feedback allowed (i.e. routing SubChannelA to
      SubChannelB and then to SubChannelC and that back to SubChannelA is not
      allowed as it would create a loop).
    </para>

    <para>
      For the instruments in the orchestra to be able to route out to the Mixer,
      a special pseudo-opcode must be used for the output of the instrument,
      entitled "blueMixerOut". You use blueMixerOut in the same way as the outc
      opcode. If the Mixer is not enabled in the Dialog, when Blue goes to
      process the instrument, blueMixerOut will be replaced with outc, thus
      making the audio of that instrument directly route out to dac or disk,
      depending on how Csound is set to render. If the Mixer is enabled,
      blueMixerOut is translated into global variables and the Mixer's
      instrument code is generated automatically without the user having to worry
      about the code details of setting up a Mixer system themselves in Csound
      code.
    </para>

    <para>
      There is also a subChannel form of blueMixerOut available that is able to
      target a subchannel by name. This form is used in the following way:
    </para>

    <programlisting>
      blueMixerOut "subChannelName", asig1, asig2 [, asig3...]
    </programlisting>

    <para>
      Using this form, the asig signals will be mixed into the subChannel given
      by name. This form is available to use within Instruments but is also very
      useful to use when working Sound SoundObjects and AudioFile SoundObjects,
      which do not have channels created for them. This way, you can route the
      output of an AudioFile to a named subchannel and apply Effects, etc.
    </para>

  </section>

  <section id="mixerEffects">
    <title>Effects</title>

    <para>
      Effects in Blue are implemented as User-Defined Opcodes, and understanding
      of how User-Defined Opcodes work in Csound is recommended before creating
      Effects. Understanding how UDO's work however is not necessary if one
      simply wants to use Effects.
    </para>

    <para>
      The workflow for using Effects with your Mixer channels is:

      <orderedlist>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Populate your Effects Library by either creating effects or
            importing them from BlueShare.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            In the Mixer, choose either the pre-fader or post-fader effects bin
            to add effects. Right click on the bins to open up a popup menu that
            shows effects that are currently in your library from which to
            choose to insert.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            In the Mixer, choose either the pre-fader or post-fader effects bin
            to add effects. Right click on the bins to open up a popup menu that
            shows effects that are currently in your library from which to
            choose to insert.
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Configure your effect by double-clicking it in the effects bin.
            Double-clicking the effect will open up a dialog that shows the
            effect's graphical user interface.
          </para>
        </listitem>

      </orderedlist>

    </para>


    <simplesect>
      <title>Effects Library</title>

      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Effects Library</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/effectsLibrary1.png" format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>
        Effects are created and managed in your Effects Library, which is
        accessible from the Tools menu. The Effects Library is program wide, so
        any Effect in the library will be accessible to use from any project you
        are working on.
      </para>

      <para>
        In the picture above, you will see the library where one can create
        Effects as well as organize them into groups. The organization into
        groups within the library will be reflected in the Effects popup that
        appears when the user is looking to add Effects to their Mixer channels.
      </para>

      <para>
        To add a group or new Effect, right click on any node and choose the
        option from the popup. The popup will also allow you to cut/copy/paste
        groups or Effects which is useful when reorganizing or when creating new
        Effects based on older ones.
      </para>

      <para>
        Once an Effect or group is added, you can edit the the name by
        double-clicking the node in the tree. Selecting an effect by clicking it
        once will populate the editor on the right. The picture above shows the
        User Interface editor for the Effect. Like other BlueSynthBuilder-based
        editors in Blue, clicking Edit Enabled will allow you to move between to
        edit modes, one in which you can add, remove, and move around widgets,
        and another where you can interact with the widgets (useful for setting
        an initial value for the Effect.)
      </para>

      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo>Effects Library</screeninfo>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/effectsLibrary2.png" format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>
        In the code editor for the Effect, one sees that the xin and xout lines
        of the User-Defined opcode display according the number of in and out
        audio signals the Effect will support. The names of the signals are
        hard-coded, which makes it easier for others to know exactly what the
        incoming and outgoing signals will be should they look at your code.
      </para>

      <para>
        Code for the Effect should follow the same principles as User-Defined
        Opcodes(i.e. one can add a setksmps line at the top of the code area).
        Values from the widgets follow the same principles as BlueSynthBuilder,
        and code completion for opcodes (ctrl-space) and BSB widgets
        (ctrl-shift-space) work within the code editor.
      </para>

      <note>
        <title>Note</title>
        <para>
          Blue currently expects Effects to have nchnls number of channels in
          and out where nchnls is the number set by the project.
        </para>
      </note>

    </simplesect>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Other Notes</title>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          The Extra Render Time option in the Mixer dialog allows the user to
          add extra time to the end of the score. This is useful to allow time
          for Effects which may have time delay (i.e. 3-second long reverb) to
          have time enough for processing, as well as simply to add time at the
          end of a piece.
        </para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Sends</title>

    <para>
      Besides effects, users are also able to put in Sends into the pre- and
      post-fader Effects bins. Sends will output the signal from that point in
      the channel's signal chain to a selected SubChannel. As with the output
      channels, Sends can only feed-forward down the chain to the Master Out and
      can not be made to create a feedback loop. Users are able to set the
      channel to send to as well as the amount to send. This send amount is also
      able to be Automated, just as the Effects are.
    </para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Randomization</title>

    <para>
      Widget values are able to be randomized in the same way as in the 
      BlueSynthBuilder, and is available in the usage mode when working with 
      Effects in the Effects Library or when using Effects from the mixer.
      Please further information, please see the documentation for 
      <link  linkend="bsbWidgetRandomization">BlueSynthBuilder Widget 
        Randomization
      </link>.
    </para>

  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Code Generation Optimization</title>

    <para>
      Blue's mixer system optimizes when generated code for Csound to use. When
      compiling down to ORC code, Blue checks all signal paths to see if any
      path will result in unused audio and if so, will optimize out any code
      that is along that path. The rules for optimization are as follows:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If channel does not generate signal to channel output (if no
          automation for level fader and fader == -96.0f), only generate code up
          to last send in preFader effects chain
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          When processing Sends, checks down the graph to see if send signal
          will make it to the Master output or not, checking both down graph of
          output channels as well as sends for each channel. If not, does not
          generate output for Send.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          If channel does not have channel output and no valid prefader sends,
          do not generate anything for channel.
        </para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>
          If SubChannel has no signal inputs (whether it's from another
          Channel's out channel, a Send, or dependency from code that uses the
          subChannel form of blueMixerOut), do not generate anything for
          channel.
        </para>
      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

  </section>

</section>
