<section id="clojureObject">
  <title>ClojureObject</title>

  <screenshot>
    <screeninfo>ClojureObject</screeninfo>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/clojureObject.png" format="PNG" scalefit="1" 
                   width="100%" contentheight="100%" />
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>ClojureObject</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>

  <para>Accepts NoteProcessors: yes</para>

  <para>
    Allows using the 
    <ulink url="http://www.clojure.org">Clojure</ulink> programming language 
    to generate score data. The Clojure interpreter is included with Blue, so 
    ClojureObjects are portable between systems without any external 
    dependencies. Users do not have to install anything further to use this 
    object, and the code will continue to function for the duration of Blue's
    existence.
  </para>

  <para>When writing your script to generate notes, assign the string value of 
    the notes to the symbol 'score'. Blue will then read in the value from 
    that variable and continue processing.
  </para>

  <simplesect>
    <title>Example 1</title>

    <programlisting>
(def score "i1 0 2 3 4 5")
    </programlisting>
    
    <para>
      The above example shows the simplest script and  will generate a single
      note. 
      If the ClojureObject is set with a start time of 0 and a duration of 2, 
      then it will generate the following score:
    </para>

    <programlisting>
i1	0.0	2	3	4	5
    </programlisting>

  </simplesect>
  
  <simplesect>
    <title>Example 2</title>

    <programlisting>
(use '[clojure.string :only (join)])

(defn pchadd [base interval] 
    (vector (+ (base 0) (quot interval 12)) (+ (base 1) (rem interval 12))))

(defn arpeggiate [totalDur instr dur basepch intervals amp]
    (let [score-template "i%d %s %s %s %s"
          notes (cycle 
                    (map #(apply format "%d.%02d" (pchadd basepch %1)) 
                        (concat intervals (subvec intervals 1 (- (count intervals) 1)))))]
    (join \newline
        (map #(format score-template instr %1 dur %2 amp) 
            (range 0 totalDur dur) ; list that will limit the map
            notes))))

(def score (arpeggiate blueDuration 1 0.25 [8 0] [0 4 7] -12))
    </programlisting>
    
    <para>
      The above example is taken from blue/examples/soundObjects/clojureSoundObject.blue.
      This script defines an apreggiate function, then calls that assigns the
      value to score.  Notice the use of blueDuration, a symbol that is automatically
      assigned to the duration of the ClojureObject.</para>
      
    <para>If the ClojureObject is set with a start time of 0 and a duration of 4, 
      then it will generate the following score:
    </para>

    <programlisting>
i1	0.0	0.25	8.00	-12
i1	0.25	0.25	8.04	-12
i1	0.5	0.25	8.07	-12
i1	0.75	0.25	8.04	-12
i1	1.0	0.25	8.00	-12
i1	1.25	0.25	8.04	-12
i1	1.5	0.25	8.07	-12
i1	1.75	0.25	8.04	-12
i1	2.0	0.25	8.00	-12
i1	2.25	0.25	8.04	-12
i1	2.5	0.25	8.07	-12
i1	2.75	0.25	8.04	-12
i1	3.0	0.25	8.00	-12
i1	3.25	0.25	8.04	-12
i1	3.5	0.25	8.07	-12
i1	3.75	0.25	8.04	-12
    </programlisting>

  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title>Regarding Processing</title>
    <para>
      Blue processes soundObjects by going through each SoundLayer and 
      generating score for each object within each layer. This is useful to 
      know so that if you are using a ClojureObject that has utility functions 
      that you later use in other ClojureObjects, you should put that utility 
      ClojureObject on the first SoundLayer closest to the top, or at least on a 
      layer above all others that contain ClojureObjects.
    </para>
    <para>
      Also to note, as a feature, Blue uses a single interpreter instance for 
      processing Clojure code. Therefore, if one ClojureObject has code evaluated, 
      the values from that code can be read by other objects. This allows 
      creating utility ClojureObjects. However, one can use stale values (or 
      values from another project even) if one is not careful to always assign 
      values in the project that require being set for this particular project.
    </para>
  </simplesect>

  <simplesect>
    <title>Variables from blue</title>

    <para>The following variables are avaialable from blue:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <title>Variables from blue</title>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>blueDuration</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Duration of the Clojure SoundObject
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>blueProjectDir</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The location of the current project's directory. Includes path separator at end.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

  </simplesect>
  
  <simplesect>
    <title>Process at Start</title>
    
    <para>
      There is a checkbox entitled "Process at Start". Selecting this option 
      will have the script of the ClojureObject run when a .blue project is 
      loaded. This is useful for scripts that act as library functions, but 
      themselves do not generate any notes. For example, you might define a 
      number of score generation utility functions in one ClojureObject that has 
      "Process at Start" enabled. Your other ClojureObject may then use the 
      functions from that ClojureObject Next time you load your project, if that 
      ClojureObject hasn't been run, your other ClojureObject will not be able to 
      be run either. If you are rendering from the beginning of a project, this 
      won't be an issue, but if you're starting work in the middle of a project, 
      you will need to evaluate that utility ClojureObject at least once. You can 
      either do a run from the start at least once, use the "Test" button to 
      have that evaluated, or use "Process at Start" and have blue ensure it is 
      loaded into the Clojure interpreter when you load your projects.
    </para>
  </simplesect>

</section>