<section id="externalSoundObject">
<title>External SoundObject</title>
       
<para>Accepts NoteProcessors: no</para>
       
<para>Allows you to write script within blue and execute an external program on
that script, bringing in generated notes back into blue. There is a field for
'command line' as well as a text area for your script. When this soundObject is
called for generating it's notes, it will write the text within the text area
into a temp file and then use the user-supplied 'command line' to execute on
that temp file.</para>
  
<para>When blue runs the commandline, it defaults to appending the temp file's
name to the end of the commandline. For example, if you wrote a perl script in
the text area and used a commandline of "perl", then when blue runs the command,
it would be something like "perl /the/path/to/the/tempFile". If you need to
explicitly put the name of the temp file somewhere else in the command line than
the end, you can use "$infile" in your commandline. For example, if you needed
something like "myCommand somefileName -w -d --some-other-flags" and had to have
it in that order, you could type "myCommand $infile -w -d --some-other-flags"
and blue will replace that $infile with the temp file's name instead of
appending it to the end.</para>

<para>When designing your scripts that you will be using with external programs,
you should either set commandline flags to the program or script your script in
a way that it will write out to stdout(to the screen), as that is what blue will
capture and bring in as notes.</para>

<para>A second method for the external object was created for bringing in score
data after running the commandline as some programs (i.e. Cmask) do not have any
possible way to write directly to stdout. The process is to use "$outfile" in
the commandline to pass in a filename to the program. That $outfile will be the
name of a temp file that the external program will write score data into. After
the program is finished, blue will open up that temp file, read in the score
data, and then remove the temp file. So, if your program needed a commandline of
something like "myProgram -i inputfilename -o outputfilename" and no options for
writing to screen, then you could use a commandline of "myProgram -i $infile -o
$outfile".</para>
      
<para>There is a test button that you may use to check to see that blue properly
brings in the generated notes.</para>


<simplesect>
<title>Command Lines and Notes Other Programs</title>

<para>This is a list of commandlines to use when using other programs with blue
and any notes that may concern other programs when being used with blue. These
commandlines assume that the programs being called are on the system path. If
not on the path, please append the full path to the program before the program
name.</para>

<variablelist>
<title>Command Lines for Programs</title>

<varlistentry>
<term>CMask</term>

<listitem>

    <para>Homepage: <ulink url="http://www.bartetzki.de/en/software.html">http://www.bartetzki.de/en/software.html</ulink> for the Linux, Windows and old Mac builds,
    <ulink url="http://www.anthonykozar.net/ports/cmask/">http://www.anthonykozar.net/ports/cmask/</ulink> for OSX 
    Author: Andre Bartetzki</para>

    <para>Comandline to use:</para>
    
    <programlisting>cmask $infile $outfile</programlisting> 

</listitem>

</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>nGen</term>

<listitem>

    <para>Homepage: <ulink url="http://mikelkuehn.com/index.php/ng">http://mikelkuehn.com/index.php/ng</ulink> 
    Author: Mikel Kuehn</para>
    
    <para>Comandline to use:</para>
    
    <programlisting>ngen $infile $outfile</programlisting>

</listitem>

</varlistentry>


<varlistentry>
<term>AthenaCL</term>
<listitem>
    <para>Homepage: <ulink url="http://www.flexatone.org/athena.html">http://www.flexatone.org/athena.html</ulink> 
    Author: Christopher Ariza</para>
    <para>Comandline to use:</para>
    <programlisting>python athenaPipe.py $infile</programlisting>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>

<para>Examples of the External SoundObject, as well as athenaPipe.py, can be 
  found in the blue/examples/soundObjects folder.</para>  

</simplesect>


</section>
