<section id="pianoRoll">
<title>PianoRoll</title>

<para>Accepts NoteProcessors: yes</para>

<screenshot>
<screeninfo>Piano Roll - Notes</screeninfo>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/pianoRoll_notes.png" format="PNG" /></imageobject>
<textobject><phrase>Piano Roll - Notes</phrase></textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>

<simplesect>
<title>About the PianoRoll</title>
<para>The PianoRoll SoundObject is a graphical tool to enter in notes, commonly available in many
MIDI sequencer environments. This PianoRoll is unique in that it is Microtonal: it supports loading
any <ulink url="http://www.huygens-fokker.org/scala/">Scala</ulink> scale file and editing of notes
adapts to that scale.  For example, in the picture above, the scale loaded is a Bohlen-Pierce scale
with 13 tones to the tritave. The PianoRoll above has adapted to that scale to show 13 scale degrees
per octave of its editor. The generated notes can output values as either frequency or PCH notation
(octave.scaleDegree).  But don't worry, if you're not interested in alternate tunings, the PianoRoll
is set by default to use 12-TET tuning, the "standard" tuning system in use today.</para>
</simplesect>

<simplesect>
<title>About Note Template Strings</title>
<para>
  The PianoRoll uses Note Template strings as a way to maintain flexibility and
  be able to handle the open-ended nature of Csound's instruments. Since the
  user who builds the instrument designs what each pfield will mean(besides p1,
  p2, and p3), the Note Template string should be made to match the instrument
  the user wants to use the PianoRoll with. When the note is generated, certain
  special text values (those enclosed in &lt; and &gt;) will be replaced by
  values unique to the note.
</para>

<para>For example, the following Note Template string:</para>

<programlisting>
i&lt;INSTR_ID&gt; &lt;START&gt; &lt;DUR&gt; &lt;FREQ&gt; 0 1 1
</programlisting>

<para>
  Will have the &lt;INSTR_ID&gt; replaced with the value set in the Piano Roll
  properties, &lt;START&gt; replaced the start time for the note, &lt;DUR&gt;
  replaced with the duration of the note, and &lt;FREQ&gt; replaced with either
  a frequency or PCH value, depending on how the Piano Roll is configured in its
  properties. The other values will pass through as part of the note.
</para>

<warning>
<title>Warning</title>

<para>
  Caution should be used when creating a Note Template string to make sure that
  there are enough spaces allowed between replacement strings. For example, the
  following:
</para>

<programlisting>
i&lt;INSTR_ID&gt; &lt;START&gt; &lt;DUR&gt; &lt;FREQ&gt; &lt;FREQ&gt; 0 1 1
</programlisting>

<para>
would result in:
</para>

<programlisting>
i1 0 2 440 440 0 1 1
</programlisting>

<para>
while the following:
</para>

<programlisting>
i&lt;INSTR_ID&gt; &lt;START&gt; &lt;DUR&gt; &lt;FREQ&gt;&lt;FREQ&gt; 0 1 1
</programlisting>

<para>
which does not have proper space between the two &lt;FREQ&gt; tags, results in:
</para>

<programlisting>
i1 0 2 440440 0 1 1
</programlisting>

</warning>

</simplesect>

<simplesect>
<title>Piano Roll Properties</title>

<para>
  The PianoRoll requires a bit of configuration before using. The properties
  page below shows the properties that should be configure before using the
  actual note drawing canvas.
</para>

<screenshot>
<screeninfo>Piano Roll - Notes - Properties</screeninfo>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/pianoRoll_properties.png" format="PNG" /></imageobject>
<textobject><phrase>Piano Roll - Notes - Properties</phrase></textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>

<variablelist>
<title>PianoRoll Properties</title>

<varlistentry>
<term>Instrument ID</term>
<listitem>
<para>
  Instrument name or number to be used when replacing &lt;INSTR_ID&gt; in Note
  template strings.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Note Template</term>
<listitem>
<para>
  The default note template when inserting notes. Notes make a copy of this
  template string when created and edits to the note's string stay with the
  note. Generally, you'll want to create a template string that will match the
  instrument this PianoRoll will be used with.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Scale</term>
<listitem>
<para>
  The scale used with this PianoRoll. The PianoRoll defaults to a 12-TET scale,
  the "standard" scale in use in Western classical and popular music. Pressing
  the button labeled "..." will open a file browser for selecting Scala scales
  to use in place of the default. After selecting a scale, the PianoRoll will
  adjust the note canvas for the number of scale degrees the newly selected
  scale contains.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Base Frequency</term>
<listitem>
<para>
  The base frequency of the scale for octave 8 and scale degree 0 (8.00).
  Defaults to C below A440.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Pch Generation</term>
<listitem>
<para>
  Selects how the notes will generate their value to be used when replacing
  the &lt;FREQ&gt; tag value in a note template.  The options are:

  <variablelist>

  <varlistentry>
  <term>Frequency</term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    The value of the note's pitch expressed in terms of frequency in hertz.
    This value is calculated using the chosen Scale for the PianoRoll.
  </para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
  <term>blue PCH</term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    Value of note expressed in blue PCH, a format similar to Csound PCH but
    differs in that it does not allow fractional values.  Values are generated
    as "octave.scaleDegree" i.e. "8.22" would be octave 8 and scale degree 22
    in a scale that has 23 or more notes, or would wrap around as it does in
    Csound PCH.  If the scale had 12 scale degrees, the "8.22" would be
    interpreted as "9.10".  blue PCH is allowed as an option to be used with
    blue PCH note processors and then to be used with the Tuning NoteProcessor.
  </para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  <varlistentry>
  <term>MIDI</term>
  <listitem>
  <para>
    When this Pch Generation method is chosen, a MIDI note value (0-127, 60 =
    Middle-C) is used for &lt;FREQ&gt; and the chosen Scale will not be used.
    The display for the editor will automatically switch to show octaves and
    notes for standard MIDI scale values.  Using MIDI note values is useful
    for instruments that exepct MIDI note values such as the fluidsynth opcodes
    as well as midiout.
  </para>
  </listitem>
  </varlistentry>

  </variablelist>

  </para>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>

</simplesect>

<simplesect>
<title>Time Options</title>

<screenshot>
<screeninfo>Piano Roll - Notes - Time Options</screeninfo>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/pianoRoll_notes_snap.png" format="PNG" /></imageobject>
<textobject><phrase>Piano Roll - Notes - Time Options</phrase></textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>

<para>The Time Options in the PianoRoll are accessed and behave very much in the same manner as those
that are in the main timeline.  The button labelled "..." in the upper right corner of the PianoRoll
canvas will open and close the panel on the right that contains the properties.</para>

<variablelist>
<title>Time Options</title>

<varlistentry>
<term>Snap Enabled</term>
<listitem>
<para>Enables snapping behavior on the timeline.  If enabled, vertical lines will be drawn at snap
points, set by the value below it. In the screenshot above, the snap is enabled and set to every 1.0
beats.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Time Display</term>
<listitem>
<para>Controls how the time in the time bar above the PianoRoll canvas will display. The time value
will show as time, while Number display will display as integers.  The number below show how often
to put a label. In the screenshot above, the Time Display is set to show a label in units of time and
at every 5.0 seconds. </para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>

</simplesect>

<simplesect>
<title>Using the Note Canvas</title>

<para>To enter notes, hold down the shift key and press the left mouse button down on the canvas.
A note will be entered where you pressed and will be set to resize as you move the mouse around.
When you finally release the mouse, the note will be finished entering.</para>

<para>After that, you can select notes by clicking on them or drag and selecting notes by marquee.  You
can also press the shift key and click on notes to add to the currently selected notes.
You can then drag the notes around by click a selected note and dragging.  To resize a note, select
a single note, and after hilighted, move the mouse to the right edge of the selected now, and then
click and drag.</para>

<para>To remove a note or notes, select the notes, then press the del key.</para>

<para>To cut or copy a note, select a single note (only one note in the buffer is currently
supported), then press ctrl-x or ctrl-c to cut or copy, respectively.</para>

<para>To paste, ctrl-click on the PianoNote canvas. (This is the same behavior as pasting
soundObjects on the main score timeline.)</para>

<para>To edit a note's template, select a single note as shown below.</para>

<screenshot>
<screeninfo>Piano Roll - Notes - Note Selected</screeninfo>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/pianoRoll_note_selected.png" format="PNG" /></imageobject>
<textobject><phrase>Piano Roll - Notes - Note Selected</phrase></textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>

<para>After selecting a note, the text field for editing the note's template text will be enabled.  Here
you can then edit the note's values.</para>

<note>
<title>For more Information</title>
<para>See the example .blue file in the blue/examples/soundObjects folder.</para>
</note>

</simplesect>



</section>
