<section id="tracker">
	<title>Tracker</title>

	<para>Accepts NoteProcessors: yes</para>

	<screenshot>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="images/tracker.png" format="PNG" />
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
	</screenshot>

	<simplesect>
		<title>About the Tracker</title>
		<para>
			The Tracker SoundObject is a table-based tool to enter in
			patterns of notes using the Tracker paradigm but in a way
			specific to Csound SCO work. Each Tracker is organized in
			vertical Tracks of n number of steps where n is configurable
			by the user (defaults to 64 steps). Notes are entered into
			each Track with Tracks being configurable as to what
			parameters (columns) to use. Unique to the blue Tracker
			SoundObject is the support for microtonal scales using Scala
			scale files as well as support for Csound's Tied-Notes
			feature.
		</para>
	</simplesect>

	<simplesect>
		<title>Introduction to the Interface</title>
		<para>
			The interface consists of three main areas: the top tool
			bar, the main tracking area, and the track properties
			editor.
		</para>
		<para>
			The top tool bar has a "+" button which adds new tracks to
			the Tracker, a Steps entry widget to enter in the number of
			steps the Tracker should have, a toggle for using Keyboard
			Note mode (see below for more information), an Octave entry
			widget to determine the relative octave for the Keyboard
			Note mode, a Test button to see what the generated score
			will be for the Tracker, as well as a help button that opens
			up a quick reference sheet for keyboard shortcuts.
		</para>
		<para>
			The main tracking area is where all of the score work is
			done to enter and modify notes. More information about note
			entry and modification is available below in the section
			"Entering in Notes".
		</para>
		<para>
			The last interface area is the track properties editor. The
			track properties editor is held in a collapsible pane and
			when the tracker editor initially loads it will be
			collapsed. To open up the track properties, at least one
			track needs to be added to the tracker. Once one track
			exists, click the small button above the right scroll bar to
			open and close the track editor properties. More information
			on using the properties editor follows below in the section
			"Settings Things Up".
		</para>
	</simplesect>

	<simplesect>
		<title>Setting Things Up</title>

		<para>
			When the Tracker Object is edited it is completely blank. To
			start, click the "+" button to add as many tracks as you
			would like to use. After adding the number of tracks you'd
			like to use you will need to configure the track to work
			with your Csound instruments. Open up the track properties
			editor using the "&lt;" toggle button above the right scroll
			bar. Afterwards, select a track by clicking the name panel
			above a track. Selecting a track will populate the track
			properties editor as well as hilight the name panel with a
			green border. A track's properties consist of a Name, Note
			Template, Instrument ID, and Columns; descriptions of the
			values are listed below.
		</para>

		<variablelist>
			<title>Track Properties</title>

			<varlistentry>
				<term>Name</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The name property is used only for reference;
						editing the name changes the title shown on the
						name panel and is for the user's reference.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>


			<varlistentry>
				<term>Note Template</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						The note template is used when generating the
						notes for the track. Items in the template that
						are within &lt; and &gt; tags will be replaced
						by values either from the Tracker (START and
						DUR), the Instrument ID (INSTR_ID) or values
						from the columns, using the column's name as a
						key (i.e. if a column is called "space", when
						generating a note for the track, any value in
						the space column will replace the &lt;space&gt;
						text in the note template). Note templates will
						generally follow the form "i &lt;INSTR_ID&gt;
						&lt;START&gt; &lt;DUR&gt;" and then have tag
						keys for each column for the track.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>


			<varlistentry>
				<term>Instrument</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Instrument name or number to be used when
						replacing &lt;INSTR_ID&gt; in Note template
						strings.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

			<varlistentry>
				<term>Columns</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Each track has a minimum of one configurable
						column (the tied-note is a feature of all tracks
						and is not a part of this editor) and is
						user-configurable to add as many columns as the
						user needs for the values to use in their notes
						for their instruments. Columns are added and
						removed using the Columns table and can be
						organized by pushing up and down in the table
						which will move their order left and right in
						the main tracking area. To edit the name of the
						Column, use the Columns table to edit the name
						of the column.
					</para>
					<para>
						Each Column also has a type. The type
						information is used by the tracker when entering
						data to verify that the data being input is of
						that column's type, as well as used when using
						shortcuts to manipulate data in that column.

						<variablelist>
							<title>Column Properties</title>

							<varlistentry>
								<term>PCH</term>
								<listitem>
									<para>
										Csound PCH format. Entering data
										will verify that data is in the
										octave.pitch format. Using the
										increment and decrement value
										shortcuts will propertly add or
										subtract one to pitch value,
										i.e. incrementing the value of
										8.11 will result in 9.00.
									</para>
								</listitem>
							</varlistentry>

							<varlistentry>
								<term>blue PCH</term>
								<listitem>
									<para>
										The blue PCH format is like the
										Csound PCH format except that
										the pitch part is always a whole
										number integer and is the scale
										degree of the selected Scale. A
										valid value in Csound PCH such
										as 8.01 is not valid in Blue PCH
										as 01 is not an integer (the
										equivalent in blue PCH would be
										8.1).
									</para>

									<para>
										Using blue PCH allows for using
										Scala scale files to do
										microtonal tracking. To choose a
										Scala scale, use the "..."
										button to open up a file
										selector to choose a Scala
										scale. Afterwards, enter in the
										base frequency for the scale
										(the default is 261.62558 or
										middle-c). The "output
										frequencies" checkbox will
										determine how the values entered
										into this column will be
										interpreted. By default, "output
										frequencies" is enabled, meaning
										when the tracker goes to
										generate notes, it will take the
										blue PCH values that are entered
										and convert them to a frequency
										value in hertz. If you deselect
										this option, the tracker will
										pass the blue PCH value out.
										This option should generally be
										left enabled unless the user is
										planning to do further operation
										on the pch values via
										NoteProcessors that work with
										blue PCH.
									</para>

									<para>
										Using blue PCH, data will be
										verified on entry and
										increment/decrement value
										options will work in the same
										way as for PCH.
									</para>
								</listitem>
							</varlistentry>

							<varlistentry>
								<term>MIDI</term>
								<listitem>
									<para>
										MIDI will limit the values
										entered to whole number integers
										from 0-127. Using the increment
										and decrement value shortcuts
										will add or subtract 1 to the
										value.
									</para>
								</listitem>
							</varlistentry>

							<varlistentry>
								<term>String</term>
								<listitem>
									<para>
										The String type allows the user
										to input any value they want. No
										verification is done on entry
										and the increment/decrement
										value shortcuts will have no
										effect.
									</para>
								</listitem>
							</varlistentry>

							<varlistentry>
								<term>Number</term>
								<listitem>
									<para>
										The Number format will limit the
										values entered to only numbers.
										Values can be further restricted
										to a given range as well as to
										only use whole number integers.
										Using the increment and
										decrement value shortcuts will
										add or subtract 1 to the value.
									</para>
								</listitem>
							</varlistentry>

						</variablelist>

					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>

		</variablelist>

	</simplesect>

	<simplesect>
		<title>Entering in Notes</title>

		<para>
			Entering in data into the tracker is much like entering data
			into any other table, though learning the keyboard shortcuts
			will vastly speed up entering and modifying data. To begin
			click anywhere on a track where you would like to add a
			note. Now, begin typing to enter in a value for that note,
			then press enter when you are finished. Depending on the
			type of column you have configured, blue will verify that
			the data entered is allowable and if so it will save that
			data to the note. If the value is not allowable, the cell
			will become hilighted in red and will require you to either
			fix your input to be valid or press esc to cancel entering
			in data.
		</para>

		<para>
			When entering in data for a new note, the first time you
			enter in information for a column in the note's row, it will
			not only enter in the data for the column, but also copy
			values for all other columns from the first note that exists
			previous to the note being edited. If there is no notes
			entered, some default settings will be used based on the
			column type.
		</para>

		<para>
			Like other tracker systems, the duration of a note entered
			will last as long as until either the next entered note, the
			end of the pattern, or until an OFF note is encountered. So,
			for example, if a note is entered in step 0 and step 2, the
			duration of the first note will last 2 steps while the
			second note will last until the end of the pattern (62 steps
			in a default 64 step track). To enter an OFF statement, go
			to the row where you want the note to end and press
			ctrl-shift-space. This will make the row an OFF note. So, if
			a note is entered in step 0 and step 2 and an OFF is entered
			into step 1 and step 4, the first note will last 1 step
			while the second note will last 2 steps.
		</para>

		<para>
			To increment and decrement values in a cell, use the arrow
			keys to go over the cell you want to increment or decrement
			and then use ctrl-up or ctrl-down respectively to change the
			value. (NOTE: This operation operates differently for each
			column type and does nothing for the String type. Please see
			the column type information above for more information.)
		</para>

	</simplesect>

	<simplesect>
		<title>Keyboard Note Mode</title>

		<para>
			Like most trackers, the Tracker object has keyboard
			shortcuts that will allow for very quickly adding notes. To
			enable Keybaord Note mode, either click the checkbox on the
			top tool bar or use the keyboard shortcut ctrl-k. By
			enabling Keyboard Note mode, the keys on the keyboard will
			be mapped to note values much like a piano keyboard. When
			the selected cell is of type PCH, blue PCH, or MIDI,
			pressing those keys will enter in a value related the
			keyboard mapping (see Shortcuts section).
		</para>

		<para>
			The user is also able to change the base octave of the
			Keyboard Note mode. To change the octave, use either the
			spinner control on the top tool bar or use the keyboard
			shortcuts ctrl-shift-up or ctrl-shift-down. By default, the
			base octave starts at middle-c.
		</para>

	</simplesect>

	<simplesect>
		<title>Shortcuts</title>

		<table>
			<title>Keyboard Shortcuts</title>
			<tgroup cols="2">
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>Shortcuts</entry>
						<entry>Description</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>ctrl-space</entry>
						<entry>clear or duplicate previous note</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>ctrl-shift-space</entry>
						<entry>set or clear OFF note</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>ctrl-up</entry>
						<entry>increment value</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>ctrl-down</entry>
						<entry>decrement value</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>ctrl-t</entry>
						<entry>toggle note tie</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>ctrl-x</entry>
						<entry>cut selected notes</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>ctrl-c</entry>
						<entry>copy selected notes</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>ctrl-v</entry>
						<entry>paste notes from copy buffer</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>insert</entry>
						<entry>
							insert blank note into currently selected
							row, notes in current row and after are
							shifted down; if notes are at end are
							shifted off they are lost
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>del</entry>
						<entry>
							delete selected note(s), move selection to
							next row after current selection
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>backspace</entry>
						<entry>
							delete selected notes, notes after selected
							notes are shifted up to fill in place where
							deleted notes were, empty notes appended to
							end
						</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>ctrl-k</entry>
						<entry>toggle keyboard notes mode</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>ctrl-shift-up</entry>
						<entry>raise keyboard octave by one</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>ctrl-shift-down</entry>
						<entry>lower keyboard octave by one</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>

		<table>
			<title>Keyboard Note Mode</title>
			<tgroup cols="4">
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>Shortcut</entry>
						<entry>PCh Value</entry>
						<entry>blue PCH Value</entry>
						<entry>MIDI Value</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>

					<row>
						<entry>z</entry>
						<entry>8.00</entry>
						<entry>8.0</entry>
						<entry>60</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>s</entry>
						<entry>8.01</entry>
						<entry>8.1</entry>
						<entry>61</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>x</entry>
						<entry>8.02</entry>
						<entry>8.2</entry>
						<entry>62</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>d</entry>
						<entry>8.03</entry>
						<entry>8.3</entry>
						<entry>63</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>c</entry>
						<entry>8.04</entry>
						<entry>8.4</entry>
						<entry>64</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>v</entry>
						<entry>8.05</entry>
						<entry>8.5</entry>
						<entry>65</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>g</entry>
						<entry>8.06</entry>
						<entry>8.6</entry>
						<entry>66</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>b</entry>
						<entry>8.07</entry>
						<entry>8.7</entry>
						<entry>67</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>h</entry>
						<entry>8.08</entry>
						<entry>8.8</entry>
						<entry>68</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>n</entry>
						<entry>8.09</entry>
						<entry>8.9</entry>
						<entry>69</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>j</entry>
						<entry>8.10</entry>
						<entry>8.10</entry>
						<entry>70</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>m</entry>
						<entry>8.11</entry>
						<entry>8.11</entry>
						<entry>71</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>q</entry>
						<entry>9.00</entry>
						<entry>9.0</entry>
						<entry>72</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>2</entry>
						<entry>9.01</entry>
						<entry>9.1</entry>
						<entry>73</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>w</entry>
						<entry>9.02</entry>
						<entry>9.2</entry>
						<entry>74</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>3</entry>
						<entry>9.03</entry>
						<entry>9.3</entry>
						<entry>75</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>e</entry>
						<entry>9.04</entry>
						<entry>9.4</entry>
						<entry>76</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>r</entry>
						<entry>9.05</entry>
						<entry>9.5</entry>
						<entry>77</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>5</entry>
						<entry>9.06</entry>
						<entry>9.6</entry>
						<entry>78</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>t</entry>
						<entry>9.07</entry>
						<entry>9.7</entry>
						<entry>79</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>6</entry>
						<entry>9.08</entry>
						<entry>9.8</entry>
						<entry>80</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>y</entry>
						<entry>9.09</entry>
						<entry>9.9</entry>
						<entry>81</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>7</entry>
						<entry>9.10</entry>
						<entry>9.10</entry>
						<entry>82</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>u</entry>
						<entry>9.11</entry>
						<entry>9.11</entry>
						<entry>83</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>i</entry>
						<entry>10.00</entry>
						<entry>10.0</entry>
						<entry>84</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>9</entry>
						<entry>10.01</entry>
						<entry>10.1</entry>
						<entry>85</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>o</entry>
						<entry>10.02</entry>
						<entry>10.2</entry>
						<entry>86</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>0</entry>
						<entry>10.03</entry>
						<entry>10.3</entry>
						<entry>87</entry>
					</row>

					<row>
						<entry>p</entry>
						<entry>10.04</entry>
						<entry>10.4</entry>
						<entry>88</entry>
					</row>



				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>


	</simplesect>

	<note>
		<title>For More Information</title>
		<para>
			See the tracker.blue example file in the
			blue/examples/soundObjects folder.
		</para>
	</note>

</section>