<section id="parameterAutomation">
  <title>Parameter Automation</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>
      Blue allows for a few ways to enter in values to automate parameters over
      time. The parameters that can be automated are those in BlueSynthBuilder
      Instruments, Mixer Effects, Mixer Sends, and Mixer Volumes. The following
      sections will describe how to use Parameter Automation and technical
      details in how this all works within the context of Blue and Csound.
    </para>

  </section>


  <section>
    <title>Available Parameters</title>

    <para>
      Besides the Volume sliders in the mixer and level amount on mixer sends,
      the following GUI Parameters are automatable when found in
      BlueSynthBuilder instruments and Mixer Effects:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>
        <para>Knob</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>HSlider</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>HSliderBank</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VSlider</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VSliderBank</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>XYController</para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para>Dropdown</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Checkbox</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>


  </section>


  <section>
    <title>Assigning Parameters</title>

    <para>
      Automations for Parameters are assignable to SoundObject LayerGroup Layers 
      that exist in the root Score by selecting from the popup menu that appears when
      selecting the "A" button on a SoundLayer's panel (on the left of the
      timeline). The menu shows what Parameters are available to use from
      Instruments and the Mixer. Those with normal color text are Parameters
      which are not currently automated, those in green are ones currently
      automated in that SoundLayer, and those in orange are ones which are
      currently automated on a different SoundLayer. Selecting normal color text
      will enable automation for that parameter on the SoundLayer, while
      selecting a green colored text one will disable automation for that
      parameter, and selecting an orange one will move it from the layer it is
      currently on to the one being worked with.
    </para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Score Timeline Modes</title>

    <para>The Score timeline has three different modes:</para>

    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Score</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This is the primary mode for adding and editing SoundObjects.
            Parameter Automations will be drawn but are not editable in this
            mode.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Single Line</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This is the primary mode for editing line points for Parameter
            Automations. The user is able to edit a single line at a time per
            SoundLayer, and can enter and remove points, modify points by 
            dragging them, as well as selecting a region and move the the points
            by dragging the region.  While dragging the region, the region will
            show that data will overwrite the area dragged to.  This overwriting 
            will not be committed however until the user releases the mouse 
            button.
            
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Multi Line</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This is the mode for selecting and moving line points for all
            Parameter Automations on a single or multiple SoundLayers. The
            use can click and drag to create a selection region, then click within
            the selection region to move all points from all lines within the
            region. While dragging the region, the region will
            show that data will overwrite the area dragged to.  This overwriting 
            will not be committed however until the user releases the mouse 
            button.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

  </section>


  <section>
    <title>Editing Automations</title>

    <para>
      To edit line values in a Parameter Automation, first switch to Single Line
      mode. Then, for the desired SoundLayer, select which of the assigned
      parameters to edit. This can be done either by using the SoundLayer Edit
      Panel's Parameter selector (found on the second row below the row with
      mute, solo, etc.; only shown when SoundLayer size is greater than 1), or
      by right-clicking the SoundLayer in the main area and selecting from the
      popup menu (the actively editable Parameter Automation will be disabled
      from the popup menu).
    </para>

    <para>
      Once a parameter is selected, the user can change the color of the line by
      using the color box next to the parameter selector panel on the SoundLayer
      Edit Panel. To add new points, use the mouse and mouse over to where you
      would like to add a point and press the left mouse button. After pressing,
      the point will be added, and the user can drag to modify the just entered
      point. Releasing the button will complete the addition of the line point.
      To edit an existing point, mouse over a point until it is highlighted in
      red, then press the left mouse button, drag, and release when finished. To
      remove an existing point, mouse over a point until it is highlighted and
      press the right mouse button.
    </para>

    <para>
      To manipulate data for a single automation, use shift-drag to select a region of the automation 
      data. Once selected you can ctrl-c to copy and ctrl-click to paste that data. You can also 
      drag the selection to move the region or drag at the edges to scale the automation data. ctrl-z 
      may be used to undo the above changes. 
    </para>

    <para>
      For finer control over the line points, right-click on the parameter line
      panel when not over an existing line point. A popup menu will appear and
      select "Edit Line Points". A dialog showing a table of line points with
      time values in one column and parameter values in a second column. The
      user can then enter in values by text entry.
    </para>

    <para>For changes of automation data for an entire layer or set of layers, use multi-line mode. 
    This will alow you to select, copy/paste, drag, and resize automation data.  If shift is used when 
    making a selection, it will also select underlying ScoreObjects. This will allow you to move both 
    automation and ScoreObject data together. If you the selected region completely contains ScoreObjects 
    (i.e., no part of any selected ScoreObjects extend outside of the region) you can also scale the 
    automation and ScoreObject data together.
    </para>

  </section>


  <section>
    <title>Technical Details</title>

    <para>
      Blue's parameter automation system is implemented in Csound code in a few
      different areas. For instruments and effects, when an Automatable
      Parameter is not set for automation, it will replace its replacement key
      in its ORC code with a constant value from the UI item. If the parameter
      is set to allow automation, then the replacement key is replaced with a Blue
      generated global k-rate signal name. Therefore, when coding instruments
      and effects, the user should be careful to make sure that if they want the
      parameter to be automatable that the replacement key is placed in the code
      where a k-rate signal is legal to use. If the user is not expecting to
      automate that value, then it would be safe to place that replacement key
      wherever a constant is allowed. This is also useful to know when migrating
      older BSB Instruments and Effects to be used with the purpose of
      Automation.
    </para>

    <para>
      After setting up the Instrument and Effects, Blue will then handle
      compiling the automations into a way that works with Csound. Currently,
      Blue will first calculate init statements from where the render start time
      is and add that to the CSD to make sure that the global krate signals will
      be initiated by the time any instrument could use them. Then, Blue creates
      instruments for each parameter that will be automated. The instruments are
      driven by score and either an instrument for continuous data or resolution
      dependent data will be created. Score is then generated for the parameter
      automation data that together with the instruments generated will create
      the signals.
    </para>

    <para>
      Care was taken to optimize the generated score and instruments.
      Unnecessary score will not be generated if multiple points with the same
      value are found as well as when there is a discontinous break in the
      values. Values from the parameter automation will also correctly be
      generated from render start time until render end time (if used). For
      parameters with resolution, every value is a discrete jump, so the
      instrument for resolution based parameters will on it's i-time run will
      simply set the new value and then turn the instrument instance off to save
      CPU cycles.
    </para>

  </section>



</section>

