<section id="conceptsPolyObjects">
<sectioninfo>
  <author><firstname>Michael</firstname><surname>Bechard</surname></author>
  <authorinitials>MB</authorinitials>
  <pubdate>2005</pubdate>
  <title>PolyObjects</title>
  <titleabbrev>PolyObjects</titleabbrev>
  <revhistory>
     <revision>
        <revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
        <date>2005.05.05</date>
        <revremark>First version of article.</revremark>
     </revision>
  </revhistory>
</sectioninfo>

<section>
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
	PolyObjects are, in my opinion, one of the most powerful tools in
	blue. They provide encapsulation of any grouping of SoundObjects,
	any way you like, into one logical SoundObject. Once encapsulated,
	the rest of blue's powerful features (namely NoteProcessors) can be
	leveraged against the PolyObject, and that is when one really begins
	to realize the benefits of using PolyObjects.
</para>

</section>

<section>
<title>Basic</title>

<simplesect>
<title>Explanation</title>

<para>
	To repeat what is stated in the reference documentation, a
	PolyObject can be seen as a container of other SoundObjects. It
	contains its own series of SoundLayers, just like the main score,
	and, like the main score, one can add as many SoundLayers and
	SoundObjects as one likes to a PolyObject.
	</para>

<para>
	Think of the main score as a big box that holds sounds. Now, we can
	put whatever sounds we want in the box, but we can also put smaller
	boxes inside the main box; these smaller boxes are our PolyObjects.
	We can put sounds inside the smaller boxes, just like we can in the
	big box, and we can arrange them in the same manner too. When we put
	sound A in the upper-right corner of a smaller box, it will stay in
	that corner no matter where we move our box inside of the bigger
	box. However, it is the position and arrangement of the sounds
	themselves relative to the main score that is important and is,
	ultimately, the reason to use PolyObjects. With sound A in the
	upper-right corner of our small box, its relative position in the
	main box will be dependent on the smaller box's position in the big
	box. Keep in mind, too, that we can put boxes inside of boxes inside
	of boxes, as many layers as we like. And when you realize that you
	can change the sounds inside of any box by applying a NoteProcessor
	to it (like making the box metal instead of cardboard), you begin to
	see the power of using PolyObjects.
</para>

</simplesect>

<simplesect>
<title>Usage</title>

<para>
	The way it works is, you
	create a PolyObject in a SoundLayer like you would any other
	SoundObject; by right-clicking on the SoundLayer and selecting "Add
	New PolyObject;" it should be at the very top. After doing this, the
	PolyObject is empty and will not generate any notes in its current
	state. You have to double-click on it in order to edit the contents
	of the PolyObject. Once you're editing the empty PolyObject, the
	score editor looks a lot like it does when you're editing an empty
	blue score. That's because the main score is just one big container
	for notes, like PolyObjects (in fact, in the code, the main score IS
	a PolyObject).
</para>

<para>
	You can see which container you are currently editing by looking at
	the buttons just underneath the tabs for "score," "orchestra," etc.
	When you're editing the main score, there will only be one button
	there called "root;" you're editing the root container. When you're
	editing a PolyObject called "Group A," you'll see two buttons;
	"root" and "Group A." Pressing any of these buttons will change the
	view to edit that container.
</para>

<para>
	Once a PolyObject has been created, you can add and arrange
	SoundObject on it just like you do in the main score. Each
	PolyObject is going to have its own Snap and Time Display settings
	too, so you may want to set those accordingly. Add SoundLayers just
	as you would in the main score too.
</para>

<para>
	After you've added all of the notes you wish to the PolyObject,
	click on the "root" button and feel free to move the PolyObject
	around in the main score, just as you would any other SoundObject.
	Add NoteProcessors too, or alter the Time Behavior; these changes,
	in turn, will be applied to the contents of the PolyObject.
</para>

</simplesect>

</section>

<section>
<title>Advanced</title>

<para>
	Before tackling some of the more advanced concepts of PolyObjects, a
	couple of clarifications must be made. When this document refers to
	editing the actual PolyObject, that means editing it as a
	SoundObject (moving it around on the timeline, stretching it,
	editing its properties, etc.). This is very different from editing
	the contents of said PolyObject. The distinction will be made in
	this section whenever applicable.
</para>

<section>
<title>Time</title>

<para>
	PolyObjects can have their Time Behavior changed like any other
	SoundObject when one is editing the actual PolyObject. This is very
	important to keep in mind, because your sounds within the PolyObject
	may span 10 beats, but if you leave the Time Behavior settings for
	the PolyObject to the default (Scale), they may in actuality span
	only two beats, depending on the size of your PolyObject. One can
	test this with the Test button: shrink a PolyObject that has the
	Scale Time Behavior and the notes within it will shrink as well.
</para>

<simplesect>
<title>No Special Time Behavior</title>

<para>
        There are a couple of easy ways to make sure
	that the sounds you place in a PolyObject remain to scale in the
	parent container, or the root score. One method is to right-click on
	the PolyObject itself and click "Set Subjective Time to Objective
	Time." This will change the length of the PolyObject to be equal to
	the beat at the end of the last SoundObject within it. In other
	words, it will expand or contract to the actual total length of all
	of the notes within it. The other method is to change the Time
	Behavior of the PolyObject to None. Blue will not do any processing
	of the length of the notes within the PolyObject; they'll just be
	played exactly the way they are in the PolyObject.
</para>

<para>
	There are advantages and disadvantages to each method. The first is
	good because it allows one to see the actual length of the
	PolyObject within the main score, but you have to remember to click
	"Set Subjective Time to Objective Time" each and every time you make
	a change to the PolyObject's contents. If you set the Time Behavior
	to None, the length of the PolyObject may appear to be two beats,
	but it may actually be ten or 20 or whatever; you don't know until
	you edit the contents of that PolyObject. However, with a Time
	Behavior of None, you can edit the contents of the PolyObject
	frequently and drastically without having to worry if your changes
	will be accurately represented in the CSD rendering. A good way to
	work may be to set a new PolyObject's Time Behavior to None and edit
	the contents of it as much as you like. Then, when it sounds
	satisfactory, you can click "Set Subjective Time to Objective Time"
	on it, so that you may edit the rest of the score while having an
	accurate picture of the actual length of the PolyObject. Keep in
	mind that you may use the "Set Subjective Time to Objective Time"
	feature on any SoundObject with any Time Behavior setting.
</para>
</simplesect>

<simplesect>
<title>Repeat/Looping Time Behavior</title>

<para>
        One can lay down a series of sounds in
	a PolyObject and setup the PolyObject to loop them. The Time
	Behavior of the PolyObject itself needs to be set to Repeat, and the
	notes will loop for as long as the PolyObject's length. When the
	PolyObject's contents actually start looping in relationship to each
	other is determined by the Repeat Point; one can edit the Repeat
	settings in the property box of any SoundObject. The Repeat Point
	specifies the beat at which the group of notes will begin after the
	previous note group begins. If the Use Repeat Point is not checked,
	the next note group will begin immediately after the previous note
	group's last note ends.
</para>

<para>
	An example would be a PolyObject whose contents are three one-beat
	notes played back-to-back:

<screen>
i1 0.0 1.0 3 4 5
i2 1.0 1.0 3 4 5
i3 2.0 1.0 3 4 5
</screen>

	If one set the Time Behavior to Repeat without using a Repeat Point
	and stretched the length of the actual PolyObject to six beats, six
	one-beat notes would play back-to-back, like this:

<screen>
i1 0.0 1.0 3 4 5
i2 1.0 1.0 3 4 5
i3 2.0 1.0 3 4 5
i1 3.0 1.0 3 4 5
i2 4.0 1.0 3 4 5
i3 5.0 1.0 3 4 5
</screen>

	However, if one were to change the PolyObject to use Repeat Points
	and set the repeat point to 2.5, this would be the result:

<screen>
i1 0.0 1.0 3 4 5
i2 1.0 1.0 3 4 5
i3 2.0 1.0 3 4 5
i1 2.5 1.0 3 4 5
i2 3.5 1.0 3 4 5
i3 4.5 1.0 3 4 5
i1 5.0 1.0 3 4 5
</screen>

	Note that there are more notes being played this time. Why? Because
	with a Time Behavior of Repeat, blue will try to fit as many notes
	that it can into the PolyObject using the repeat settings given,
	without violating the order and length of the PolyObject's note
	arrangement. With the previous example, blue played the second group
	of three notes at beat 2.5, and realized it could squeeze in a
	partial third loop. This third loop begins at beat five, since that
	is equivalent to beat 2.5 in the second loop, which is our Repeat
	Point. It inserted the first note there and realized it couldn't fit
	any more notes, since the next note would begin at beat six and play
	until beat seven; that's longer than the length of our PolyObject,
	which is six.
</para>

</simplesect>
</section>

<section>
<title>NoteProcessors and PolyObjects</title>

<para>
	NoteProcessors are great when used in conjunction with PolyObjects.
	They can be very powerful, but you have to be careful of a few
	gotcha's.
</para>

<simplesect>
<title>P-fields and PolyObjects</title>

<para>
        One thing to be aware of with
	PolyObjects and NoteProcessors are p-fields. The user must make sure
	that the p-field(s) that is being operated on by the Note
	Processor(s) is the same for all sounds within the PolyObject. If
	one has a lot of typical notes in a PolyObject where p4 equals the
	pitch, and one errant note where p4 equals phase, for instance,
	things could get disastrous if one tries to apply a PchAddProcessor
	to the whole PolyObject. Please refer to the Best Practices section
	for more information.
</para>
</simplesect>

<simplesect>
<title>Time Behavior and NoteProcessors</title>

<para>
        Everything
	that is to follow in this section can be summed up in one important
	fact: NoteProcessors get applied to SoundObjects before the Time
	Behavior does. What this means is, if you have a PolyObject with
	Repeat Time Behavior and set it up to loop twice, and have a
	LineAddProcessor on that same PolyObject, you will have a group of
	notes looped twice with the LineAddProcessor behavior applied twice;
	that is, applied individually to each looped group of notes.
</para>

<para>
	So, to borrow from the example in Repeat/Looping Time Behavior, our
	group of three notes with no NoteProcessor and no Repeat Point would
	render like this:

<screen>
i1 0.0 1.0 3 4 5
i2 1.0 1.0 3 4 5
i3 2.0 1.0 3 4 5
i1 3.0 1.0 3 4 5
i2 4.0 1.0 3 4 5
i3 5.0 1.0 3 4 5
</screen>

	If I add a LineAddProcessor to p-field four, starting from zero and
	going to two, here's what the result would look like:

<screen>
i1 0.0 1.0 3.0 4 5
i2 1.0 1.0 4.0 4 5
i3 2.0 1.0 5.0 4 5
i1 3.0 1.0 3.0 4 5
i2 4.0 1.0 4.0 4 5
i3 5.0 1.0 5.0 4 5
</screen>

	This may be the desired effect, and it may not. In order to apply a
	NoteProcessor after the Time Behavior has been applied, take the
	following steps:

<orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	<para>
	Apply the Time Behavior to you PolyObject, with no NoteProcessor
	on it.
	</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	<para>
	Right-click on the PolyObject and select "Convert to
	PolyObject." What this will do is embed your PolyObject in yet
	another PolyObject.
	</para>
	</listitem>

	<listitem>
	<para>
	Edit the Properties of the new PolyObject and
	apply the NoteProcessor to it.
	</para>
	</listitem>

</orderedlist>

	If one applies the previous steps to
	the example cited above, the rendered notes look like this:


<screen>
i1 0.0 1.0 3.0 4 5
i2 1.0 1.0 3.4 4 5
i3 2.0 1.0 3.8 4 5
i1 3.0 1.0 4.2 4 5
i2 4.0 1.0 4.6 4 5
i3 5.0 1.0 5.0 4 5
</screen>


	One thing the user will have to keep in mind, though; when referring
	to beats, those beats will be applicable to the notes as they are
	after the Time Behavior change. So, in the previous example, in
	order to get those results, one has to change the ending beat in the
	LineAddProcessor to five instead of two, because five is the beat at
	which the last note plays in the looped sequence.
</para>
</simplesect>
</section>


<simplesect>
<title>Multi-layered Polyobjects</title>

<para>
    As mentioned previously, PolyObjects can contain other
	PolyObjects. The thing to remember when doing this is that each
	PolyObject's settings, NoteProcessor's, etc. are local to itself.
	For blue, the notes generated from a PolyObject SoundObject are the
	same as the ones generated from a GenericScore or any other type of
	SoundObject, and can be manipulated in the same way.
	</para>

</simplesect>

</section>

<section>
<title>Best Practices</title>

<simplesect>
<title>Separate notes with dissimilar behavior into their own PolyObjects</title>

<para>
	Let's say you're making a PolyObject with lots of regular notes
	whose p4 field represents the pitch. At some point you also want to
	insert a note that affects something a bit more irregular, like the
	phase of the other notes, and its p4 field represents, say, the
	amount of variance in the phase. It would be prudent to separate
	that irregular note away from the notes in this PolyObject in order
	to keep your expectations about the p-field of the PolyObject as a
	whole consistent. Without the irregular note, you can safely say
	that p4 of PolyObject X (or whatever its called) represents the
	pitch of all of the notes it contains. However, with that extra note
	in it, p4 has no consistent meaning in PolyObject X, and you can't
	safely apply NoteProcessors to it that affect that p-field.
</para>

</simplesect>

<simplesect>
<title>Group co-reliant notes together into PolyObjects</title>

<para>
    Co-reliant notes, in this
	case, would be notes that rely on each other to make their sound.
	For instance, if you had a group of notes that fed their output to a
	zak channel, then another note to process and play that channel's
	sound, those notes would be co-reliant. The reason to do this is to
	try to make each SoundObject in the main score independent so that
	one can move, remove, and edit each of them without worrying about
	affecting other notes. The PolyObjects, effectively, begin to
	represent one atomic sound in your score, making it easier to
	experiment with.
</para>

<para>
	Doing this also allows one to reliably freeze PolyObjects. If one
	tried to freeze a PolyObject that did nothing but write its output
	to a zak channel, the resulting sound file would be dead silence,
	and the score would never work (since a frozen sound does nothing
	but read and play a sound file).
</para>

</simplesect>

<simplesect>
<title>Wait, what about separating dissimilar notes?</title>

<para>
    That's still possible with co-reliant but
	dissimilar notes. What one would do, to use the example in the
	previous section, is make a PolyObject that contained the instrument
	processing the zak channel output and another embedded PolyObject.
	The embedded PolyObject would then contain all of the actual notes
	writing to the zak channel. Now what you can do is apply all kinds
	of NoteProcessors to the embedded PolyObject, then freeze or do
	whatever to the parent PolyObject in a reliable fashion.
</para>
</simplesect>

<simplesect>
<title>Try to group logical phrases in your music into PolyObjects</title>

<para>
    It's much
	easier on the user as a composer to arrange the notes this way. This
	enables one to see opportunites for reuse of certain musical
	phrases, and implement that repetition easily by adding said
	PolyObjects to the SoundObject Library and copying instances
	wherever they're needed.
</para>

</simplesect>

<simplesect>
<title>Try to keep the length of the PolyObject	representational of its actual length</title>

<para>
    This only really applies if
	the Time Behavior being used is None, otherwise a PolyObject's
	length is always going to represent accurately its length in the
	composition. Remember to use "Set Subjective Time to Objective Time"
	as needed.
</para>

</simplesect>

</section>

<section>
<title>Debugging</title>

<para>When things don't work out the way you expected
	them too (and they won't), a great tool to use to help track down
	the problem is the "Test" button. This button renders the
	i-statements that any given SoundObject will generate, and it comes
	in very useful with PolyObjects. So, if you've got a PolyObject that
	won't render when you Test it, drill down into it and test its
	constituent notes, Testing and drilling down into its
	sub-PolyObjects as well. You'll eventually find the cause. Examine
	NoteProcessors and the Time Behaviors of each SoundObject; these can
	be common culprits with sound problems too.
</para>

<para>
	If one follows the best practice "Group co-reliant notes together
	into PolyObjects," this also makes it easier to debug problems. You
	can isolate PolyObjects in the main score easily by soloing that
	SoundLayer, etc. (since they won't rely on other SoundObjects for
	their sound) and investigate the problem that way; many times,
	you'll find that the problem stems from the PolyObject not being as
	independent as you'd thought.
</para>

</section>

</section>

