<section id="soundObjectLibrary">
  <title>SoundObject Library</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>
      The SoundObject Library is a place to store SoundObjects either
      project-wide or program-wide. The project-wide library can be used to store a
      SoundObject that you may want to user later but it also enables Instance
      SoundObjects to be made. Instances of SoundObjects point to the
      SoundObject in the library and when the instance generates its score, it
      will call the SoundObject in the library to first generate score and then
      apply its own properties and NoteProcessors to the generated score.
      Updating a SoundObject in the library will then update all instances of
      that SoundObject. This feature is useful to represent the idea of a
      motive, with instances of the motive allowing to have transformations by
      use of NoteProcessors.
    </para>

    <para>
      The program-wide library (called "User SoundObject Library" in the interface)
      allows one to build up a catalog of reusable SoundObjects. SoundObjects such
      as Sound and ObjectBuilder allow users to build highly configurable sound
      and score generators that have a high degree of reusability.  The program-wide
      library is also where SoundObjects are exported from and imported to with BlueShare.
    </para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>
      The general pattern of usage for the project-wide SoundObject Library entails:

      <orderedlist>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Add SoundObject to the Library. This is done by selecting a
            SoundObject, right-clicking the SoundObject to open up the popup
            menu and selecting "Add to SoundObject Library". 
          </para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>
            After doing this, your SoundObject will have been added to the
            library and the SoundObject on the timeline will have been replaced
            with an Instance SoundObject which will be pointing to the
            SoundObject now in the library.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>
            At this point, the user can now take advantage of the library by 
            making copies of the instance object on the timeline and pasting in
            more instances.  These instances can be placed anywhere, have 
            different durations and time behaviors, as well as have their own
            individual NoteProcessors.  This allows expressing ideas such as
            "This is an instance of the primary motive (SoundObject in the 
            library) but transposed up a major 3rd, retrograded, and inverted", 
            or an idea like "I've got drum pattern A in the library and I have
            instances of it here and here and ...".
            
            <note>
              <title>Note</title>
              <para>
                When copying and pasting Instance SoundObjects, they are all
                pointing to the SoundObject in the library.
              </para>
            </note>
            
          </para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>
            You can also then make instances of SoundObjects in the library by
            opening up the SoundObject Library dialog (available from the 
            Window menu or by using the F4 shortcut key).  There you have 
            the following options:
            
            <variablelist>

              <varlistentry>
                <term>Copy</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    This makes a copy of the selected SoundObject and puts it in
                    the buffer. This is a copy of the original SoundObject and
                    not an Instance. After copying to the buffer, you can paste
                    as normal on the timeline.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Copy Instance</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    This makes a Instance of the selected SoundObject and puts
                    it in the buffer. This Instance will point to the original
                    SoundObject. After copying to the buffer, you can paste as
                    normal on the timeline.
                  </para>

                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
              
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Remove</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    This will remove the selected SoundObject from the library.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
                                          
            </variablelist>
            
          </para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>You can also then edit the SoundObject in the library from 
            within the SoundObject Library dialog by selecting the SoundObject
            in the list.  The editor for the SoundObject will appear below.  
          
            <note>
              <title>Note</title>
              <para>
                Editing the SoundObject in the library will affect all instances of
                that SoundObject.
              </para>
            </note>
          
          </para>
          
        </listitem>

      </orderedlist>

    </para>

    <para>
      The general pattern of usage for the program-wide SoundObject Library entails:

      <orderedlist>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            Add SoundObject to the Library. This is done by selecting a
            SoundObject on the timeline, right-clicking the SoundObject to open up the popup
            menu and selecting "Copy". 
          </para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>
            After copying an object, open up the SoundObject library window and go to the
            User SoundObject Library. Right-click a folder node in the library tree and 
            choose "Paste" to add a copy of the object to the library. 
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>
            You can use the context popup menu to create new folders, or double-click a 
            node to rename the node.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        
      </orderedlist>

    </para>

  </section>

</section>
