<section id="buildingBlue">
  <title>Building blue</title>


  <section>
    <title>Requirements</title>

    <para>To build blue, the following programs are used:</para>

    <variablelist>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Java Development Kit 1.4+</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Contains javac java compiler and other development tools.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Apache Ant or Apache Maven</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            blue comes with both an Apache Ant build file as well as an Apache
            Maven (1.0.x) build file. Either can be used to build blue from the
            commandline, though the user can also easily import the sources and
            libraries of blue into an IDE (i.e. Netbeans, Eclipse, Idea) and use
            the IDE's project build system.
          </para>

          <para>
            The Maven build file is mostly used when doing releases, while the
            Ant build file will be more useful for those who are simply wanting
            to build and use blue.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>JUnit</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            JUnit is required to run the unit tests and is integrated as part of
            the build.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>IzPack</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            IzPack is used for building the blue installer jar; if you are not
            building an installer, this library won't be necessary.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>xsltproc, Apache FOP, Sun JAI library</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            xsltproc is used to build all versions of the manual. To build the
            PDF manual, Apache FOP and Sun JAI library are required.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

  </section>



  <section>
    <title>Getting the Sources</title>

    <para>
      To build blue, you will either need to download a src.zip file from the
      Soureforge release server or use CVS to download the latest sources.
    </para>

  </section>


  <section>
    <title>Maintaining a Version of blue from CVS</title>

    <para>
      After checking out from CVS and building, one should modify the
      appropriate starter script in the blue/bin directory for your platform to
      correctly point to BLUE_HOME. After that, running CVS update and
      rebuilding using Ant should keep you up to date.
    </para>

    <note>
      <title>Note</title>
      <para>
        While checkins to CVS are almost always done in such a way that the
        program is in a state which it will compile and function cleanly, it
        sometimes does happen that a broken checkin occurs. Users building from
        CVS should be careful to depend on using only a version from CVS if they
        are not able to fix code to make things compile. If you are not able to
        fix Java code, then it is recommended to keep two copies of builds from
        CVS, one which to use for your general use and another for using to test
        if things will build.
      </para>
    </note>



  </section>

</section>